<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.27</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Patrician</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4389450</id>
    <revision>
      <id>946717786</id>
      <parentid>927556420</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-21T23:55:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Robert1947</username>
        <id>3501582</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* 1957–1958 */ space and period</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12465" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:PackardPatrician1953.jpg|thumb|275px|1953 Packard Patrician photographed and used by the Packard Motors Company in its advertisements for the automobile model]] --&gt;
The '''Packard Patrician''' is an automobile which was built by the [[Packard|Packard Motor Car Company]] of [[Detroit]], Michigan, from model years 1951 through the 1956.  During its six years in production, the Patrician was built in Packard's Detroit facilities on [[Packard Automotive Plant|East Grand Boulevard]]. The word "[[Patrician (ancient Rome)|patrician]]" is Latin for a ruling class in [[Ancient Rome]].

==Packard Patrician 400, 1951–1952==

{{Infobox automobile
| image = Packard Patrician 400 2552 4-Door Sedan 1952.jpg
| caption = 1952 Packard Patrician 400
| name = Packard Patrician 1951-1952
| manufacturer = [[Packard]]
| production = 1951–1952
| predecessor = [[Packard Super Eight]]
| successor = 
| layout= [[FR layout|FR]]
| body_style = [[Sedan (automobile)|Sedan]]
| engine = Packard [[Straight-eight engine|Straight Eight]] &lt;br&gt;{{convert|327|cuin|abbr=on}}, 150&amp;nbsp;bhp (112&amp;nbsp;kW)
| transmission = [[Ultramatic]]
| length = 5580 mm (219,70 in)
| width = 1990 mm (78,3 in)
| height = 1580 mm (62.2 in) 
| weight = 
| wheelbase = 3226 mm (127 in) 
| track = 
| related = [[Packard Mayfair]]&lt;br&gt;[[Packard 400]]
| designer = 
}}

In 1951 and 1952, the automaker attempted to use a numeric naming structure that designated Packard's least expensive models as [[Packard 200]] and 200 Deluxe while two-door hardtop and convertibles were designated Packard 250 and its mid-range sedan the [[Packard 300]].

The highest trim level available was the Packard Patrician 400.  The Patrician 400 replaced the previous model year's [[Packard Super Eight|Super 8]] model range. The car was easily identified from other Packards by its chrome trim; in 1951 the model featured three chrome ports on its rear fenders and in 1952 the car featured four chrome ports, a styling approach similar to GM's [[Buick#Ventiports|Buick]] luxury vehicles.  Patricians and 300s also sported a slightly revised grille  which included chrome "teeth" in its oval area in 1951. That change occurred to the 250 series soon after introduction.

The Patrician 400 was available only as a premium, four-door sedan, outfitted with high-grade upholstery and chrome trimming within. For the 1952 model year, Packard retained the services of noted interior decorator [[Dorothy Draper]] to bring a fresh look to the interior color scheme. Wilton carpeting and hassock-style rear passenger foot rests were also included with the car. With a list price of $3,662 it also was the most expensive regular Packard offered. The automobile rode upon a 127-inch (3226&amp;nbsp;mm) wheelbase shared only with the 300 sedan. All other Packards had a wheelbase of 122 inches (3099&amp;nbsp;mm).

Power for all Packards still came from their venerable in-line eight-cylinder engines. 200s used a {{convert|288|cuin|abbr=on}} unit with 135&amp;nbsp;bhp (101&amp;nbsp;kW); all others had a displacement of {{convert|327|cuin|abbr=on}}, delivering 150&amp;nbsp;bhp (112&amp;nbsp;kW). The Patrician got the best engine Packard had to offer, too. For unequaled smooth operation, its engine featured nine main bearings instead of five as in the other engines without increase in power.

Until 1954, [[Henney (coachbuilder)|Henney]] built a few nine-passenger Executive Sedans and Corporate Limousines on a chassis with 148-inch (3759&amp;nbsp;mm) wheelbase. [[Derham Body Company|Derham]] in Rosemont built very few Patrician Custom Formal Sedans with leather padded roofs, small backlights and elaborate interiors on the standard Patrician frame.

Introduction of the Patrician was, together with most other Packards (250s were delayed), in August 1950. Production totals for 1951 came to 9,001 Patrician 400 units, and 3,975 units for 1952.

The '''400''' model name was dropped for model years 1953 and 1954; however the Patrician name continued to occupy the premium trim level Packard from 1953 through 1956.

&lt;gallery widths="200px" heights="150px"&gt;
File:1951 Packard Patrician 400 sdn - maroon - fvr (4665798645).jpg|1951 Packard Patrician 400
File:1952 Packard Patrician (7444824866).jpg|1952 Packard Patrician 400 
&lt;/gallery&gt;

{{-}}

==1953–1954==
{{Infobox automobile
| image = 1954 Packard Patrician Touring Sedan rear left, Lime Rock.jpg
| caption = 1954 Packard Patrician 
| name = Packard Patrician 1953-1954
| manufacturer = [[Packard]]
| production = 1953–1954
| predecessor = 
| successor = 
| layout= [[FR layout|FR]]
| body_style = [[Sedan (automobile)|Sedan]]
| engine = 
| transmission =
| length = 
| width =
| height = 
| weight = 
| wheelbase = 
| track = 
| related = 
| designer = 
}}
For model years 1953 and 1954, the Patrician continued to represent Packard's highest trim level sedans and rode on the 127" chassis. The Patrician also was used for the basis of the custom bodied Henney passenger models, including the 149" wheelbase 8 passenger Packard Executive Sedans and Limousines, the difference being that the latter had a partition window between the front and rear compartments. During these years the Patrician received annual trim changes and improvements associated with model-year change-overs in the 1950s.

The Henney professional cars (hearse, ambulance, flower car, service car) built on the 156" wheelbase commercial chassis generally used Patrician-like trim except for 1954, which used [[Packard Cavalier|Cavalier]]-like trim, and was offered in a hardtop bodystyle called the [[Packard Pacific]]. Since the professional cars were fully coachbuilt bodies (not conversions) built on Packard's separate commercial chassis, their trim level had little to do with the Patrician except for the general appearance. The Henney Junior, a short-wheelbase hearse or ambulance was built on the standard Cavalier-Patrician chasses (but with stronger, heavy-duty rear suspension) but had the 5-main bearing Cavalier engine rather than the 9-main bearing engine of the Patrician.

For 1953, the Patrician used the same {{convert|327|CID|cc|adj=on}} 9-main bearing engine that used for 1951 and 1952 but for the first time added a four barrel [[carburetor]] for an increase in power. For 1954, the new {{convert|359|CID|cc|adj=on}} 9-main bearing, aluminum head {{convert|212|hp|abbr=on}} engine was standard and also featured a 4-brl carburetor. 1954 was the first year to add a start-position to the ignition key - earlier years were started by a switch built into the carburetor which was actuated by depressing the accelerator pedal to the floor.

A general description implies that all Patrician models were fitted out with standard equipment when in fact they could be built to order. If a customer wanted a manual transmission then that is what he or she would be given by the factory.

&lt;gallery widths="200px" heights="150px"&gt;
File:1953 Packard Patrician.jpg|1953 Packard Patrician
File:Four States Auto Museum April 2016 23 (1954 Packard Patrician 400).jpg|1954 Packard Patrician 
&lt;/gallery&gt;

{{-}}

==1955–1956==
{{Infobox automobile
| image = PackardPatrician 1956.jpg
| caption = 1956 Packard Patrician
| name = Packard Patrician 1955-1956
| manufacturer = [[Packard]]
| production = 1955–1956
| predecessor = 
| successor = 
| layout= [[FR layout|FR]]
| body_style = [[Sedan (automobile)|Sedan]]
| engine = Packard 6.2 1956 [[V8 engine|V-8]] &lt;br&gt;372.5&amp;nbsp;cid (6135&amp;nbsp;cc), 290&amp;nbsp;ps, 211,94kW
| transmission = [[Ultramatic#1955: Twin-Ultramatic Drive|Twin-Ultramatic]]
| length = 5580 mm (219,70 in)
| width = 1990 mm (78,3 in)
| height = 1580 mm (62.2 in) 
| weight = 2075 kg (4551,73 lbs) 
| wheelbase = 3226 mm (127 in)  
| track = 
| related = [[Packard Four Hundred]]
| designer = Richard A. Teague
}}

For 1955, the entire senior line of Packards received an extensive design update that freshened the last restyling that was done in 1951. Under designer [[Richard A. Teague]], the Senior Packards received a more modern grille design, "Cathedral"-styled rear tail lights, hooded headlight housings and a new exterior trim layout that afforded Packard the ability to offer two- and three-tone paint combinations with the simplest of masking patterns. While Packard could not afford a whole new greenhouse for the passenger compartment, new trim at the base of the rear [[Pillar (car)|pillar]] made it look like it had a redesigned roofline. The cars were also outfitted with a wrap-around windshield, thus bringing it in line with American automobiles of the era. Inside, upholstery and bright work was also freshened and the cars received a new dashboard layout. 1955 and 1956 instruments and controls were similar, but the 1955 dash featured a warm, bronze-like surface, and in 1956 were faced with a machined-look stainless steel facing.

For 1955, the Patrician was offered as a four-door sedan only and Packard produced 9,127 of the cars. Changes for 1956 included a revised headlight housing that exaggerated the front peak further forward. The area around the headlight was painted black to give the effect of greater depth. The car also received a different grille texture. During the 1956 model year, 3375 Patricians rolled off Packard's production line before the model was dropped by the ailing carmaker.

The final Packard built (that was a true Packard and not a badge-engineered Studebaker President) was a black Patrician sedan, and it rolled off the Packard assembly line on June 25, 1956.

&lt;gallery widths="200px" heights="150px"&gt;
File:1955 Packard Patrician.JPG|1955 Packard Patrician
File:1956 Packard Patrician.jpg|1956 Packard Patrician
&lt;/gallery&gt;

{{-}}

==1957–1958==
While Packard's [[James J. Nance|James Nance]] had hoped to divorce the senior Packard from its lower-priced [[Clipper (automobile)|Clipper]] models for 1956 and beyond, Studebaker-Packard's Corporate finances were far worse than Nance bargained for after the 1954 merger between the two firms. Following disposal of Packard's body supplier, Briggs, to Chrysler, Packard bought the old Connor Avenue Briggs plant to produce their own bodies and switched entire production there completely, abandoning the East Grand Boulevard plant. Quality control was terrible and because of this, and a failure by [[American Motors Corporation|American Motors]] to buy as many [[Ultramatic]] transmission units and Packard V-8's as Nance had hoped for, Packard production was eliminated at the firm's ex Briggs Detroit factory and transferred to Studebaker's South Bend complex for the 1957 model year.

The Packard V8 was used in the slow selling [[Hudson Hornet]] and [[Nash Ambassador]] for 1955 and 1956 and also the 1956 [[Studebaker Golden Hawk]].

The sole Packard offered for 1957, a badge-engineered [[Studebaker President]], was designated the [[1957 and 1958 Packards|Packard Clipper]].  A McCulloch supercharger was used with the Studebaker V8 in the Packard Hawk which was also later made. The final Packard, a car with no series name, rolled off the line in 1958 and Studebaker-Packard's Board removed the "Packard" name from its corporate name in 1962.

Bad management and particularly Mr. Christopher have been blamed for the company's demise. In fact the best management in the world could not have competed with GM s power. For example if there was no market for Cadillac 62's the same Fisher body would be switched to Buick or Oldsmobile. For example Fisher A Type bodies were Chevrolet Stylemaster, Pontiac 25 or 27 or Oldsmobile 66. B type bodies were either Pontiac 26 or 28, Buick 40 or Cadillac 61. Packard could not do that. At best they had two brands (Packard and Clipper) one ageing body, no station wagon, a new V8 to pay for, a partner in severe debt and the loss of defense contracts to GM. The result was a 35 acre waste land.

==See also==
* [[ZIL-111]]

==Further reading==
* {{cite book | editor-last=Gunnell |editor-first=John | title = The Standard Catalog of American Cars 1946-1975 | publisher = Kraus Publications | year = 1987 | isbn = 0-87341-096-3}}
* {{cite journal |last=Hamlin |first=George L. |title=1951-1954 Packard, American New Choice in Fine Cars |journal=Collectible Automobile |date=February 1992 |volume=8 |number=5 |pages=56–69}}
* Pierson, Don, [http://www.packardimperial.com/ Packard / IMPERIAL page]

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]</text>
      <sha1>dupy55s9bjz6489vjksdloyuz5etcr2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Station Sedan</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4429016</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868351517</id>
      <parentid>821807244</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-11T17:05:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TKOIII</username>
        <id>31772205</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>tag</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1678" xml:space="preserve">{{Single source|date=November 2018}}[[File:Packard Station Sedan at 2015 Macungie show 1of5.jpg|thumb|right|1949 Packard Station Sedan]]

The '''Packard Station Sedan''' was a pseudo [[station wagon]] model produced by the [[Packard|Packard Motor Car Company]] of [[Detroit, Michigan]] between 1948 and 1950, using the [[Packard Super Eight]] platform.  By offering the Station Sedan, Packard could market a vehicle with station wagon attributes, but without the full investment costs associated with a full-blown station wagon program development.
==History==
The Station Sedan used a combination of steel framing and body parts along with structural wood panels to create a "[[Woodie (car body style)|woody]]" station wagon-like car.  Unlike other woody wagons of the day, which used wooden passenger compartments mounted to chassis of a particular car, the Station Sedan used a steel subframe and steel passenger doors onto which hard wood panels were mounted. The only wooden door on the vehicle was the rear gate assembly.
[[File:Packard Station Sedan at 2015 Macungie show 4of5.jpg|thumb|1949 Packard Station Sedan cargo area]]
Neither a sedan, nor true station wagon, the Station Sedan enjoyed limited success and was discontinued when the 1951 Packard models were introduced.

==Further reading==
* {{cite book | author = Gunnell, John, Editor | title = The Standard Catalog of American Cars 1946-1975 | publisher = Kraus Publications | year = 1987 | isbn = 0-87341-096-3}}

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}
{{commonscat}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Station Sedan]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]
[[Category:Station wagons]]


{{Classicpow-auto-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>3wjw3xzvf1phxpy224hjpuf2mlg3hxt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard One-Twenty</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4444204</id>
    <revision>
      <id>949674046</id>
      <parentid>925762519</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-04-07T21:13:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iridescent</username>
        <id>937705</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */Cleanup and [[WP:AWB/T|typo fixing]], [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: 1929-1936 → 1929–1936</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="15188" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox automobile
| name = Packard One-Twenty
| image  = 1936 Packard Custom Convertible Victoria - LeBaron - fvl.jpg
| caption = 1936 Packard 120 Convertible Victoria by [[LeBaron Incorporated|LeBaron]]
| manufacturer = [[Packard]]
| assembly = [[Packard Automotive Plant]], [[Detroit]], [[Michigan]], [[United States]]
| class = [[Full-size]] [[luxury car]]
| successor = [[Packard 200]]          
| model_years = 1935–1937&lt;br/&gt;1939–1941
| layout = [[Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive layout|Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive]]
}}

The '''Packard One-Twenty''' (also known as the '''One Twenty''' and '''120''') is an automobile produced by the [[Packard|Packard Motor Car Company]] of [[Detroit]], [[Michigan]], from 1935 to 1937 and from 1939 through the 1941 model years. The One-Twenty model designation was replaced by the [[Packard 200]].

The One-Twenty signified the first time that Packard had entered into the highly competitive mid-priced eight-cylinder car market. Packard enthusiasts view the production of the One-Twenty and the [[Packard One-Ten|Six/One-Ten models]] as the start of Packard's losing its hold on the market as the premier American luxury automotive brand. It was a marketing strategy shared with GM's [[LaSalle (automobile)|LaSalle]], the [[Chrysler Airstream]], and the [[Lincoln-Zephyr]]. It was introduced after Rolls-Royce brought to market the [[Rolls-Royce Twenty|Rolls-Royce 20]], which was manufactured between 1922 and 1929, and replaced by the [[Rolls-Royce 20/25]] which was built between 1929–1936.

The introduction of the One-Twenty (and later the Six/One-Ten models) was a necessary move to keep Packard in business during the final years of the [[Great Depression]], expanding on an earlier approach with the [[Packard Light Eight]]. Branding the One-Twenty a Packard afforded buyers the cachet of owning a Packard, a name long regarded{{By whom|date=April 2016}} as one of America's most prestigious cars. Other reasons the company decided to forgo the development of a companion brand name to sell the less expensive models may have been linked to its single production line capability at its Grand Boulevard manufacturing plant or to the expense of launching a new brand of automobile. It also ushered in a novel advertising approach, commissioning an advertising "jingle" called "[[When Heaven Was at the Corner of Sycamore and Main]]".

== The ''Safe-T-Flex'' suspension ==
This car introduced the [[independent front suspension]] to the Packard line. Its so-called "Safe-T-Flex" suspension was an [[Double wishbone suspension|unequal upper and lower A-arm type]] with the largest possible lower A-arm composed of two different arms bolted together at a ninety-degree angle.&lt;ref name="1936 Packard 120 Owner's Manual"&gt;{{cite web|title=1936 Packard 120 Owner's Manual|url=http://packardinfo.com/xoops/html/modules/article/view.article.php?224|website=packardinfo.com|accessdate=22 August 2015|pages=37–39|format=pdf|date=December 1935}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The support arm was a heavy steel [[forging]] reaching a few degrees forward of lateral from the front wheel support to as close to the centerline of the car as is practicable. An integral pad socketed the helical spring, whose upper end reached a high frame cross-beam. A tubular, hence lighter, steel torque arm was bolted to the support arm somewhat inboard of the wheel to permit a sufficient steering arc. It reached the frame nearly at the dashboard with a spherical rubber bearing. The upper A-arm was conventionally welded and oriented parallel to the lower one. Between it and the frame was an old-fashioned horizontal [[shock absorber]] whose two cylinders were side by side.&lt;ref name="1936 Packard 120 Owner's Manual" /&gt;

The support arm carried all the load; the torque arm carried the accelerating and decelerating torque; the upper A-arm controlled the [[Camber angle|camber]]. Advantages claimed for the system included superior maintenance of [[wheel alignment]] from the wide spread of the lower A-arm, a permanent fixing of the [[caster angle]], and an increased percentage of the braking force transmitted to the frame through the torque arm.&lt;ref name="1936 Packard 120 Owner's Manual" /&gt;

== First generation (1935–1937) ==
{{Infobox automobile
| name              = First generation
| image             = Packard One Twenty 4-Door Sedan 193X.jpg
| caption           = 1937 Packard One-Twenty Touring Sedan
| model_years   = 1935–1937
| body_style      = {{unbulleted list|2-door [[coupé]]|2-door [[convertible]]|2-door [[Sedan (automobile)|sedan]] (1935 only)|4-door [[Sedan (automobile)|sedan]]}}
| layout             = [[Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive layout|Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive]]
| related            = [[Packard Eight]]
| engine            = {{unbulleted list|{{convert|257|cuin|L|1|abbr=on}} [[Straight-eight engine|I8]] (1935)|{{convert|282|cuin|L|1|abbr=on}} [[Straight-eight engine|I8]] (1936–37)}}
| transmission  = 3-speed [[Manual transmission|manual]]
| wheelbase     = {{convert|120|in|mm|1|abbr=on}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=1935 Packard 120 Series|url=http://classiccardatabase.com/specs.php?series=654&amp;year=1935&amp;model=18124|website=Classic Car Database|accessdate=29 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| length            = 
| width              = 
| height            = 
| weight            = 
}}

In its introduction year, the Packard One-Twenty was available in a broad array of body styles including two and four-door sedans, convertible and Club Coupe. The One-Twenty, weighing in at {{convert|3688|lb|kg|abbr=on}},&lt;ref name="Old Car Advertising"&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1935/1935%20Packard%20Ad-01.jpg Old Car Advertising] Retrieved 12 September 2013&lt;/ref&gt;  was powered by an all-new Packard aluminum-head&lt;ref name="Old Car Advertising"/&gt; [[Flathead engine|L-head]] [[Straight-eight engine|inline eight]] producing {{convert|110|bhp|kW|0|abbr=on}} at 3850 rpm.{{citation needed|date=September 2013}}&lt;!--[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1930/1930%20Packard%20Ad-08.jpg Old Car Advertising] says 90hp in 1930.--&gt; Prices ranged from $980 for the three-passenger business coupe to $1,095 for the Touring Sedan. Introduced in January 1935, the car was an immediate success with consumers, with Packard producing 24,995 One-Twentys, compared to 7,000 of all other type Packards for the year.

For 1936 Packard increased the displacement on the L-head eight, increasing its output to {{convert|120|bhp|kW|0|abbr=on}}, making the car capable of reaching a top speed of {{convert|85|mph|km/h|0|abbr=on}}.  The One-Twenty added a convertible four-door-sedan model which was the most expensive model in the range priced at $1,395. A total 55,042 units rolled off the line in 1936, the highest production that the One-Twenty would reach.

In 1937, the One-Twenty went up-market as the company introduced the Packard Six, the first six-cylinder Packard in ten years. For 1937, the One-Twenty broadened its model range and was now available in "C" and "CD" trim levels.  The line also added a wood-bodied station wagon, Touring Sedan and [[limousine]] built on a {{convert|138|in|mm|abbr=on}} wheelbase&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oldcarbrochures.com/static/NA/Packard/1937%20Packard/1937_%20Packard_120_Brochure/1937%20Packard%20120-07.html |title=Directory Index: Packard/1937 Packard/1937_ Packard_120_Brochure |publisher=Oldcarbrochures.com |date= |accessdate=2012-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; and priced under $2,000. Introduced in September 1936, 50,100 units were produced during series production.

For 1938, the One-Twenty name was dropped and its model folded into the [[Packard Eight]] model range, bringing the model name into parity with the Packard Six.
&lt;!-- When introduced, the [[Packard Six|Six]], priced at around $1200,&lt;ref&gt;The price was reduced by $100 in 1938, to $1070, with [[down payment]] of $357 required that year; payments would be $35 a month, which Packard claimed was only $2-$6 more than "several smaller cars". [http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1938/1938%20Packard%20Ad-01.jpg Old Car Advertising], [http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1937/1937%20Packard%20Ad-09.html Old Car Advertising], and [http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1938/1938%20Packard%20Ad-05.html Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 5 October 2013&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Packard 120 Eight Business Coupe 1936.jpg|1936 Packard Fourteenth Series Eight 120-B 998 Business Coupé
File:Packard 120-B Convertible Sedan 1936.jpg|1936 Packard Fourteenth Series Eight 120-B 997 Convertible Sedan
File:Packard 120-C Convertible Coupe 1937.jpg|1937 Packard Fifteenth Series Eight 120-C 1099 Convertible Coupé
File:Packard 120-C 4-Door Sedan 1937.jpg|1937 Packard Fifteenth Series Eight 120-C 4-Door Sedan
&lt;/gallery&gt;

{{clear}}
== Second generation (1939–1941) ==
{{Infobox automobile
| name              = Second generation
| image             = Packard 4-Door Touring Sedan 1941.jpg
| caption           = 1941 Packard One-Twenty Touring Sedan
| model_years   = 1939–1941
| body_style      = {{unbulleted list|2-door [[coupé]]|2-door [[convertible]]|2-/4-door [[Sedan (automobile)|sedan]]|4-door [[convertible]]|4-door [[station wagon]] (1941 only)}}
| layout             = [[Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive layout|Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive]]
| related            = 
| engine            = {{convert|282|cuin|L|1|abbr=on}} [[Straight-eight engine|I8]]
| transmission  = 3-speed [[Manual transmission|manual]]
| wheelbase     = {{collapsible list|title=Models|1='''Series 1701, 1801, 1901 (1939–41):'''&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|127|in|mm|1|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name="Packard 1701"&gt;{{cite web|title=1939 Packard 120 8 Series 1701 Business Coupe|url=http://classiccardatabase.com/specs.php?series=134&amp;year=1939&amp;model=18309|website=Classic Car Database|accessdate=29 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;|2='''Series 1702 (1939):'''&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|148|in|mm|1|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name="Packard 1702"&gt;{{cite web|title=1939 Packard 120 8 Series 1702 Touring Sedan|url=http://classiccardatabase.com/specs.php?series=135&amp;year=1939&amp;model=18315|website=Classic Car Database|accessdate=29 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;|3='''Series 1801A Chassis (1940):'''&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|160|in|mm|1|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name="Packard 1801A"&gt;{{cite web|title=1940 Packard 120 Series 1801A Chassis|url=http://classiccardatabase.com/specs.php?series=7086&amp;year=1940&amp;model=18348|website=Classic Car Database|accessdate=29 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| length            = {{collapsible list|title=Models|1='''Series 1701 and 1801 (1939–40):'''&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|200.75|in|mm|1|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name="Packard 1701" /&gt;|2='''Series 1702 (1939):'''&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|221.5|in|mm|1|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name="Packard 1702" /&gt;|3='''Series 1801A Chassis (1940):'''&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|233.75|in|mm|1|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name="Packard 1801A" /&gt;|4='''Series 1901 (1941):'''&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|206.25|in|mm|1|abbr=on}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=1941 Packard 120 Series 1901 Business Coupe|url=http://classiccardatabase.com/specs.php?series=504&amp;year=1941&amp;model=18404|website=Classic Car Database|accessdate=29 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;|5='''Series 1901 Station Wagon (1941):'''&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|216|in|mm|1|abbr=on}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=1941 Packard 120 Series 1901 Station Wagon|url=http://classiccardatabase.com/specs.php?series=504&amp;year=1941&amp;model=18409|website=Classic Car Database|accessdate=29 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| width              = 
| height            = 
| weight            = 
}}

Returning to the Packard model range, the One-Twenty continued to be offered in a full range of body styles from coupe to Touring Limousine, with prices for the model range between $1,099 and $1,856. New for the year was introduction of column shifting (known in Packard parlance as Handishift), which did away with the floor shifter.  Introduced in September 1938, a total of 17,647 units were built.

In 1939, the company introduced a fifth, transverse shock absorber on the 120.&lt;ref name="oldcaradvertising.com"&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1939/1939%20Packard%20Ad-02.html Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 5 October 2013&lt;/ref&gt; It also offered Packard's Unimesh four-speed [[synchromesh]] [[Transmission (mechanics)|transmission]],
&lt;ref name="Ad-06 2013"&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1931/1931%20Packard%20Ad-06.jpg Old Car Advertising]; [http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-01.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; the same as in the [[Packard Twelve|Twelve]]&lt;ref name="oldcaradvertising.com"/&gt; (and already standard on the [[Packard Eight|Eight]]),
&lt;ref name="Ad-06 2013"/&gt;  as well as the new fourth-gear Econo-Drive [[Overdrive (mechanics)|overdrive]], claimed to reduce engine speed 27.8%, and able to be engaged at any speed over {{convert|30|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1939/1939%20Packard%20Ad-01.html Old Car Advertising], [http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1939/1939%20Packard%20Ad-02.html Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 5 October 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

The series name One-Twenty officially became hyphenated for model year 1940. Again, the One-Twenty came in a full array of body styles, including a semi-custom Convertible [[Victoria (bodystyle)|Victoria]] by [[Howard "Dutch" Darrin]]. Introduced in August 1939, total model year output was 28,138 units.

In its final year as a model, the One-Twenty lost a number of body styles to the expanded One-Ten line of cars. The One-Twenty was available in business [[coupé]], club coupe, two-door [[Sedan (automobile)|sedan]], four-door sedan, convertible coupe, convertible sedan, and two [[station wagon]] styles. Production sank to 17,100 units.

For 1942, the One-Ten and One-Twenty were dropped as model names and their models folded into the Packard Six and Packard Eight lines. In its seven years in the Packard line-up, the One-Twenty saw a total production of 175,027 units.

&lt;gallery widths=200px heights=135px&gt;
File:Packard 1701 Eight Touring Sedan 1939.jpg|1939 Packard One-Twenty Touring Sedan (17th series)
File:Packard 1701 Police 1939.jpg|1939 Packard One-Twenty Police (17th series)
File:1940 Packard 120 Darrin Convertible, Lime Rock.jpg|1940 Packard One-Twenty Darrin Convertible Victoria (18th series)
File:1941 Packard One-Twenty 2-door Touring Sedan in Black, front left (Hershey 2019).jpg|1941 Packard One-Twenty 2-door Touring Sedan (19th series)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== Notable vehicles ==
On August 29, 1935, a Packard One-Twenty [[convertible]] driven by the Belgian king [[Leopold III of Belgium|Leopold III]] crashed in [[Küssnacht]], Switzerland, killing his wife [[Astrid of Sweden]], Queen of the Belgians.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,748959,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
{{Commons category|Packard 120}}
* {{cite book | author = Kimes, Beverly R., Editor. Clark, Henry A. | title = The Standard Catalog of American Cars 1805–1945 | publisher = Kraus Publications | year = 1996 | isbn = 0-87341-428-4}}
* Owner's Information (manual) 1936 Packard 120

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|One-Twenty]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]
[[Category:1930s cars]]</text>
      <sha1>4fqln24k219gvsoqzp7rtlti4oj59il</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard 180</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5814532</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931297543</id>
      <parentid>922601177</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-18T03:42:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelinking 1 books for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.1alpha3</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="8551" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox automobile
| name              = Packard One-Eighty
| image             = 1941 Packard 180.JPG
| caption           = 1941 Packard One-Eighty Touring Sedan
| model_years       = 1940–1942
| body_style        = {{unbulleted list|2-door [[convertible]]|4-door [[Sedan (automobile)|sedan]]|4-door [[convertible]]|4-door [[limousine]]|4-door [[Coupe de Ville|town car]]}}
| layout            = [[Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive layout|Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive]]
| related           = 
| engine            = {{convert|356|cuin|L|1|abbr=on}} [[Straight-eight engine|I8]]
| transmission      = 3-speed [[Manual transmission|manual]]
| wheelbase         = {{ubl | {{convert|127|in|mm|0|abbr=on}} | {{convert|138|in|mm|0|abbr=on}} | {{convert|148|in|mm|0|abbr=on}} }}
| length            = 
| width             = 
| height            = 
| weight            = 
| predecessor       = [[Packard Twelve]]
| successor         = {{ubl | [[Packard Clipper]] | [[Packard Super Eight|Packard Custom Eight]] }}
}}

The '''Packard 180''' was introduced for the 1940 model year (18th series) by the [[Packard]] Motor Car Company to replace the discontinued [[Packard Twelve]] as their top-of-the-line luxury model. The correct name of the model was '''Custom Super Eight One-Eighty'''. The car was derived from the [[Packard Super Eight|Packard Super Eight One-Sixty]] with which it shared the complete running gear including the [[Straight-eight engine|in-line eight-cylinder]], {{convert|356|CID|cc|adj=on}} engine that developed 160 [[horsepower]]. It was advertised as the most powerful eight-cylinder engine offered by any automobile manufacturer in 1940. (By contrast, the [[Cadillac]] 346 cubic inch V-8  developed 150&amp;nbsp;hp). It was complemented and gradually replaced by the more modern looking and expensive [[Packard Clipper]] in 1941 and fully replaced by the [[Packard Super Eight|Custom Eight]] after the war.

Packards of all series (110, 120, 160, 180) shared similar body styling in 1940 (which some later said led to a "cheapening" of the once-exclusive luxury marque), using the same bodies with hoods and front fenders of different length to meet their respective chassis. Thus the 160 and 180 got identical bodies. However, the 180s featured finer interior detailing with the best fabrics, leather and carpeting available. Packard used a special woolen ceiling in these cars only which was sewn longitudinally. Packard built the partition in its Limousines in a way that there was no hint of it when the partition glass was lowered, allowing the owner to use the car by himself as a sedan (thus the designation "Sedan Limousine" by Packard).

[[File:1940 Packard Model 1807 Formal Sedan (22826624708).jpg|thumb|left|1940 Packard One-Eighty Formal Sedan (Series 1807)]]
In 1940, Packard made [[air conditioning]] an option. It was developed by the [[Henney Motor Company]], with whom Packard had a long standing business connection. Air conditioning had been used on Henney-bodied ambulances as early as 1938. It was the first time that air conditioning was available on a stock automobile. The Packard 180 was also the first car to have [[power window]]s.

In an exclusive agreement with Packard since 1937 until Henney's demise in 1954, Henney provided bodies for Packards's [[ambulance]]s, [[hearse]]s and [[flower car]]s, and they often provided special custom body work for passenger cars. The pre-World War II Henney models usually had 160-180 trim but were actually constructed on the Packard 120A 156" wheelbase chassis with the smaller 288 cubic inch engine although there were also 160 and 180 versions available.

[[File:1942 Packard Custom Super Eight One-Eighty, front right.jpg|thumb|left|1942 Packard Custom Super Eight One-Eighty 8-passenger sedan (Series 2008)]]
There were minor styling changes in the 1941 and 1942 models (19th and 20th series), the most notable of which were the moving of the headlamps into the fenders. Also for the first time, running boards could be deleted with a rocker panel put in their place to cover the chassis, and two-tone paint schemes were available. New for 1941 was the "[[Semi-automatic transmission|Electromatic Drive]]", a vacuum-operated clutch for the manual transmission. Packard's own automatic transmission, the [[Ultramatic]], would not be ready until 1949.

The final 180s rolled off the Packard assembly line in February 1942, as production restrictions of World War II brought a halt to civilian automobile production. There have been rumors that machinery was transferred to the [[Soviet Union]], and production continued until 1959 as the [[ZIS-110]]. James Ward found no supporting evidence in the Packard archives of such a transfer.&lt;ref&gt;James Ward, The Fall of Packard, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; Also, the ZIS-110 shares no sheet metal with any Packard,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kitfoster.com/2007/08/clipper-conundrum.html |title=Kit Foster's CarPort: The Clipper Conundrum |publisher=Kitfoster.com |date=2007-08-22 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite the fact that its external decor elements were intentionally designed to heavily resemble pre-war Packards, favoured by Stalin after he had received a [[Packard Twelve]] as a gift from [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.rbth.com/lifestyle/328376-kremlin-cars-favorite-rides | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20190618210059/https://www.rbth.com/lifestyle/328376-kremlin-cars-favorite-rides | archivedate = 2019-06-18 | title = Kremlin cars: The favorite rides of Russian leaders, from Nicholas II to Putin | work = Russia Beyond | publisher =  | last = Timofeychev | first = Aleksey | date = 2018-05-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A black 1941 Packard One-Eighty Super Eight was featured in ''[[The Godfather]]''. 

{{clear-left}}
===Darrin-bodied cars===
[[File:1940 Packard 180 Convertible Victoria by Darrin, front right (Hershey 2019).jpg|thumb|left|1940 Packard One Eighty Convertible Victoria by Darrin]]
Designer [[Darrin of Paris|Howard "Dutch" Darrin]] had made a few special bodies on Packard-basis, beginning in 1937. He tried to sell Packard on the idea of Darrin-bodied cars being offered directly by Packard, and finally got his way after parking one if his creations outside the Packard dealers' annual conference.&lt;ref name=RMSdarrin&gt;{{cite web | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20191023021336/https://rmsothebys.com/en/auctions/az17/arizona/lots/r264-1940-packard-one-twenty-convertible-victoria-by-darrin/411589 | archivedate = 2019-10-23 | url = https://rmsothebys.com/en/auctions/az17/arizona/lots/r264-1940-packard-one-twenty-convertible-victoria-by-darrin/411589 | title = 1940 Packard One Twenty Convertible Victoria by Darrin | id = Lot 153 | type = Auction Catalogue | publisher = RM Sotheby's | location = Arizona | date = 19-20 January 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For the 1940 model year, three Darrin bodystyles were available: the closed four-door Sport Sedan, the four-door Convertible Sedan, and the two-door Convertible Victoria. About 100 Packard Darrins were built until 1942, when production of private cars ended because of the war. This was much fewer than planned.&lt;ref name=RMSdarrin/&gt;

Building even this number of cars would have overstretched Darrin's Hollywood workshops so they were built by American Central Manufacturing - one of the last remnants of the [[Cord (automobile)|Auburn-Cord-Duesenberg]] conglomerate - in [[Connersville]] ("Little Detroit") [[Indiana]] instead. Darrin would travel back and forth between California and Indiana supervising construction. This work was shifted to Sayers &amp; Scovill in [[Cincinnati]] (the company became [[Hess &amp; Eisenhardt]] in 1942) to let ACM concentrate on building Jeep bodies.&lt;ref name=Pfau&gt;{{citation | first = Hugo | last = Pfau | title = The Coachbuilt Packard | publisher = Darlton Watson | location = London, UK | date = 1973 | isbn = 0901564109 | url-access = registration | url = https://archive.org/details/coachbuiltpackar00pfau }}&lt;/ref&gt; Between 59 and 72 Packard Darrins were built in 1940, of which 44 (or 48) were One-Eightys and the remainder [[Packard One-Twenty|One-Twentys]].&lt;ref name=RMSdarrin/&gt; For the 1941 and 1942 model years the four-door Darrins were discontinued, leaving only the Convertible Victoria. 

{{clear-left}}
==References==
{{Reflist}}

*Ward, James A. The Fall of the Packard Motor Car Company, Copyright 1995, Page 46

==External links==
{{commons category}}

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|180]]
[[Category:Cars introduced in 1940]]</text>
      <sha1>598mspns4jrwz2tzkysmiyghgoyk8mv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Super Eight</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5827066</id>
    <revision>
      <id>926090051</id>
      <parentid>922596311</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-14T04:54:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mr.choppers</username>
        <id>8373762</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4858" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox automobile
| name              = Packard Super Eight
| image             = Packard Super Eight 1501.jpg
| caption           = 1937 Packard Super Eight
| manufacturer = [[Packard]]
| production     = 1939–1951
| assembly        = [[Packard Automotive Plant]], [[Detroit]], [[Michigan]], [[United States]]
| layout             = [[Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive layout|Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive]]
| related            = [[Packard Station Sedan]]
| body_style      = {{unbulleted list|2-door [[coupé]]|2-door [[Convertible (car)|convertible]]|4-door [[Sedan (automobile)|sedan]]}}
| wheelbase      = {{unbulleted list|{{convert|127|in|mm|0|abbr=on}} (1939)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oldcarbrochures.com/static/NA/Packard/1939%20Packard/album/1939%20Packard-24.html |title=Directory Index: Packard/1939 Packard/album |publisher=Oldcarbrochures.com |date= |accessdate=2012-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;|{{convert|120|in|mm|0|abbr=on}} (1946)&lt;ref name="oldcarbrochures1946"/&gt;|{{convert|127|in|mm|0|abbr=on}} (1949)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oldcarbrochures.com/static/NA/Packard/1949_Packard/1949_Packard_Owners_Manual/1949%20Packard%20Manual-44-45.html |title=Directory Index: Packard/1949_Packard/1949_Packard_Owners_Manual |publisher=Oldcarbrochures.com |date= |accessdate=2012-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| length             = {{convert|208|in|mm|0|abbr=on}} (1946)&lt;ref name="oldcarbrochures1946"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oldcarbrochures.com/static/NA/Packard/1946%20Packard/album/1946%20Packard-14.html |title=Directory Index: Packard/1946 Packard/album |publisher=Oldcarbrochures.com |date= |accessdate=2012-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| predecessor   = [[Packard 180]]
| successor       = [[Packard Patrician|Packard 400 Patrician]]
}}

'''Packard Super Eight''' was the name given to the larger of the two [[Straight-eight engine|eight-cylinder]] [[Luxury vehicle|luxury automobiles]] produced by the [[Packard|Packard Motor Car Company]] of [[Detroit]], [[Michigan]]. It shared frames and some body types with the top model [[Packard Twelve]]. Following the discontinuation of the Seventeenth Series Packard Twelve after the 1939 model year, a new [[Packard 180|Super Eight One-Eighty]] was derived from the Super Eight as the new top car range. The Super Eight was renamed the [[Packard 180|Packard Super Eight One-Sixty]]. These two models shared most mechanical components including the 160 HP straight Eight engine.

After 1942, Packard concentrated on the new Clipper styling that was developed for an upper-class sedan the previous year. There were Super Clippers and Custom Super Clipper in the One-Sixty and One-Eighty tradition until 1947. After a heavy facelift, the name Clipper was dropped. The most senior Super Eight One-Eighty became the Custom Eight, while its slightly lower-priced sibling, the Super Eight One-Sixty, once again became simply the Super Eight. Clipper Custom Super Eights and Custom Eights were very close relatives to their respective Super models, distinguished outside by the lack of an eggcrate grille and small rear chrome trim moulding under the trunk lid on Supers. In 1949, a new Super Eight Deluxe was added to the line. This car had also the Custom Eight's eggcrate grille, but not the rear trim.

The entire range of Packard's motorcars was renamed for the 1951 model year (twenty-fourth series), when the Super Eight was renamed [[Packard 400|400]].

==In popular culture==
A green 1938 Super Eight is the titular vehicle in [[Anton Myrer]]'s 1978 novel ''The Last Convertible'' and its 1979 television miniseries adaptation.

A yellow 1949 convertible was used in the ''[[Back to the Future]]'' franchise as Doc Brown's car.

&lt;gallery widths=200px heights=145px&gt;
File:Packard-Super-Eight-1502.jpg|1937 Packard Super Eight Convertible Sedan (model 1502), formerly belonging to [[Carol II of Romania]]
File:Packard 1502 Super Eight Touring Limousine 1937.jpg|1937 Packard Super Eight Touring Limousine (model 1502)
File:Packard 1705 Super Eight Touring Limousine 1939.jpg|1939 Packard Super Eight 1270 Touring Limousine (model 1705)
File:Packard Super 8 (Centropolis Laval '10).jpg|1939 Packard Seventeenth Series Super Eight Touring Limousine
File:1940 Packard Super Eight 160 Wagon,front right, Greenwich 2018.jpg|1940 Packard Eighteenth Series Super Eight One-Sixty Wagon
File:1941 Packard One-Sixty (Super Eight) Convertible Coupe, front left at Hershey 2019.jpg|1941 Packard Super Eight One-Sixty Convertible Coupe (19th series)
File:1948 Packard Super 8 Deluxe.jpg|1948 Packard Super Eight Deluxe 4-Door Sedan
File:Packard - Flickr - exfordy (2).jpg|1949 Packard Super Eight Convertible
&lt;/gallery&gt;

{{commonscat}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Super Eight]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]
[[Category:1940s cars]]


{{Classicprw-auto-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>62h0qs162vxkg022mbu1w21mrwruf2x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard 200</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4422533</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931490707</id>
      <parentid>928561276</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-19T05:16:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelinking 1 books for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.1alpha3</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="9910" xml:space="preserve">{{More citations needed|date=November 2010}}
{{Infobox automobile
| name              = Packard 200/250
| image             = 1951 Packard 200 Deluxe 4-door Sedan 2401-2462, front left (Hershey 2019).jpg
| caption           = 1951 Packard 200 Deluxe 4-door Sedan
| manufacturer = [[Packard]]
| assembly        = [[Packard Automotive Plant]], [[Detroit]], [[Michigan]], U.S.
| class               = [[Full-size car|Full-size]] [[Luxury vehicle|luxury car]] 
| model_years   = 1951–1952
| body_style      = '''200:'''&lt;br/&gt;{{unbulleted list|2-door [[coupé]]|4-door [[Sedan (automobile)|sedan]]}}'''250:'''&lt;br/&gt;{{unbulleted list|2-door [[hardtop]] ("[[Packard Mayfair|Mayfair]]")|2-door [[convertible]]}}
| layout             = [[Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive layout|Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive]]
| related            = {{unbulleted list|[[Packard 300]]|[[Packard Patrician|Packard Patrician 400]]}}
| engine            = {{unbulleted list|{{convert|288|cuin|L|1|abbr=on}} [[Straight-eight engine|I8]] (200 series)|{{convert|327|cuin|L|1|abbr=on}} [[Straight-eight engine|I8]] (250 series)}}
| transmission  = {{unbulleted list|3-speed [[Manual transmission|manual]]|3-speed [[Manual transmission|manual]] with [[Overdrive (mechanics)|overdrive]]|2-speed ''[[Ultramatic#1949-1954: Ultramatic Drive|Ultramatic]]'' [[Automatic transmission|automatic]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=The Auto Editors of Consumer Guide|title=1951, 1952, 1953 Packard Mayfair|url=http://auto.howstuffworks.com/1951-1953-packard-mayfair2.htm|website=[[HowStuffWorks]]|date=23 November 2007|accessdate=3 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| wheelbase     = {{convert|122|in|mm|1|abbr=on}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=1951 Packard 200 Series 2401 Business Coupe|url=http://www.classiccardatabase.com/specs.php?series=6742&amp;year=1951&amp;model=28061|website=Classic Car Database|accessdate=4 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| length            = {{unbulleted list|{{convert|209.4|in|mm|1|abbr=on}} (200 series)|{{convert|217.8|in|mm|1|abbr=on}} (250 series)}}
| width              = {{convert|77.9|in|mm|1|abbr=on}}
| height            = {{unbulleted list|{{convert|62.7|in|mm|1|abbr=on}} (200 series)|{{convert|62|in|mm|1|abbr=on}} (250 series)}}
| weight            = {{convert|3550|-|4040|lb|kg|abbr=on}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=1952 Packard 250 Series 2531 Convertible Coupe|url=http://www.classiccardatabase.com/specs.php?series=4947&amp;year=1952&amp;model=28076|website=Classic Car Database|accessdate=5 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| predecessor  = [[Packard Eight]]
| successor    = {{unbulleted list|[[Packard Clipper#1953–1956|Packard Clipper]] (coupé/sedan)|[[Packard Mayfair]] (hardtop)||[[Packard Convertible]] (convertible)}}
| designer     = John Reinhart&lt;ref name="indep"&gt;{{Cite book | title = Standard Catalog of Independents: The Struggle to Survive Among Giants | editor-first = Ron | editor-last = Kowalke | publisher = Krause Publications | ref = Indie | location = Iola, WI | page = [https://archive.org/details/standardcatalogo00ronk/page/260 260] | date = 1999 | isbn = 0-87341-569-8 | url = https://archive.org/details/standardcatalogo00ronk/page/260 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

The '''Packard 200''' was an automobile model produced by the [[Packard|Packard Motor Car Company]] of [[Detroit]], Michigan during model years 1951 and 1952. Models in the '''200''' designation represented the least expensive Packard model range, on the firm's shortest wheelbase, and least powerful {{convert|288|CID|L|1|abbr=on}} [[Straight-eight engine|8-cylinder in-line]] engine. It replaced the [[Packard One-Twenty]] and the [[Packard One-Ten]], and was renamed the [[Packard Clipper]] for the 1953 model year.

Concurrently, the company also produced the '''Packard 250''', which shared the same basic body and wheelbase as the 200, but was equipped with Packard's larger {{convert|327|CID|L|1|abbr=on}} 8-cylinder in-line engine and stylized with more upscale exterior detailing. The 250 model line consisted of the convertible and the [[Packard Mayfair|Mayfair]] hardtop.

== Overview ==
The 1951 Packard 200 and 250 were introduced as Packard's least expensive model range on August 24, 1950, taking the place of the low-line Packard Standard models which were eliminated for the 1951 model year. The 200 debuted as part of the fully redesigned Packard line, attributed to John Reinhart. Replacing the bulbous 1948-1950 Packards in the 22nd and 23rd Packard Series, Reinhart's "High Pockets" design was more formal than its predecessor, and would serve Packard until the end of the 1956 model year when true Packard production ceased.

[[File:Packard 250 Convertible 1951.jpg|thumb|left|1951 Packard 250 convertible]]
[[File:Flickr - DVS1mn - 52 Packard.jpg|thumb|left|1952 Packard 250 Mayfair hardtop]]

Both the 200 and the 250 were considered "junior" series cars, and were separated from the [[Packard 300]] and [[Packard Patrician|Packard Patrician 400]] models by their shorter wheelbases ({{convert|122|in|mm|-1|abbr=on|disp=or}} versus {{convert|127|in|mm|-1|abbr=on|disp=or}}) and lesser trim appointments. Packard 200 standard models were available as a four-door sedan, two-door coupé, and a three-passenger business coupé (lacking a rear seat). While similar in appearance to the senior cars, the junior Packard lacked the noted Packard [[cormorant]] hood ornament and had vertical tail lights instead of the horizontal units on the senior models. The junior models also lacked the wrap-around rear window feature found on senior Packard sedan models.

The 250 model range was introduced in March 1951, and was specially designed to fill the vacuum of Packard having neither a hardtop or convertible in its 1951 model range. Besides their unique body styles, 250's received three jet-louvers on each rear-quarterpanel. Better grade trim and fabric were used within.

All Packard 200 models came with twin horns, two sun visors, front and rear bumper guards, spare tire and jack set. Deluxe trim level included the spartan appointments found on the standard models, and added chrome wheel rings, and turn indications as standard. White-wall tires and full-wheel covers were also extra. The {{convert|288|CID|L|1|abbr=on|adj=on}} straight-eight produces {{convert|135|hp|kW|0|abbr=on}} at 3600&amp;nbsp;rpm with a 7.0:1 compression ratio - Ultramatic-equipped cars received a slightly higher compression ratio of 7.5:1 thanks to which it offered {{convert|138|hp|kW|0|abbr=on}}. The 327 V8 was also available as an option on the 200 for $45, considerably less than the cost of a heater/defroster.&lt;ref name="indep261"&gt;[[#Indie|Kowalke]], p. 261&lt;/ref&gt;

Items which have since become standard to the auto industry since the late 1960s such as heater, radio, tinted glass, carpeting, etc., were all optional on the Packard, as well as other premium cars during that era.  Packard also became the first car-maker to offer power-brakes in 1951. “Easamatic” as they were trademarked, were a product of [[Bendix Corporation|Bendix]] and an exclusive to Packard.

Changes for 1952 were minimal, and centered on the requisite annual trim updates. Packard did drop the Business Coupé, a move that other U.S. automakers were also making at the same time.

== Marketing legacy ==
[[File:1952 Packard Series 250 Convertible.jpg|thumb|1952 Packard 250 convertible]]
While Packard's overall sales for 1951 were over 100,000 units, too many of the units sold were low-line models in the 200 and 250 series.  Senior Packards – the traditional prewar niche that Packard ruled in the 1920s and 1930s – offered during 1951 and 1952 were only available as two models, the 300 and the Patrician 400, both of which were only available in a single body type, the four-door sedan. Dealers, who were quick to appease their customers, sold Packard 300 and Patrician 400 model trim and applied it to the lesser Packard 200 and 250 models, diluting the Senior Packards of the visual uniqueness that separated them from lesser priced cars.

To remedy this, Packard hired [[James J. Nance]], the CEO of [[Hotpoint]] to reestablish Packard as an automotive leader. Among Nance’s first moves was to begin building model identity by dropping the numeric model designations and renaming the entire range of models. Nance also saw to it that Senior Packards received broader visual cues and trim to separate themselves from lesser models.  Nance also began creating different specialty and show cars in an attempt to create "buzz" in the automotive press and make Packard look less moribund, like the [[Packard Pan-American]] and the [[Packard Panther]].

The 200 and 250 models were renamed the [[Packard Clipper|Packard Clipper Special]] and Clipper Deluxe, part of Nance’s plan to ultimately spin the cars off into their own make in 1956 as the [[Clipper (automobile)|Clipper]] and return the Packard name to a maker of strictly luxury automobiles.

== Production statistics ==
Total Packard production numbers for both years on both models:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor-last=Gunnell|editor-first=John|title=The Standard Catalog of American Cars 1946-1975|publisher=Krause Publications|year=1987|isbn=978-0-87341-096-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1951, 200 (Standard - all body styles), 24,310 units
* 1951, 200 (Deluxe - all body styles), 47,052 units
* 1951, 250 (all body styles) 4,640 units (Introduced in March 1951, partial model year tally)
* 1952, 200 (Standard - all body styles), 39,720 units
* 1952, 200 (Deluxe - all body styles), 7,000 units
* 1952, 250 (all body models), 5,201 units

== References ==
{{commonscat}}

; Inline
{{Reflist}}
; General
* {{cite journal|last=Hamlin|first=George L.|title=1951-1954 Packard, American New Choice in Fine Cars|journal=Collectible Automobile|date=February 1992|volume=8|issue=5|pages=56–69}}

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|200]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]
[[Category:Coupés]]
[[Category:Sedans]]
[[Category:1950s cars]]</text>
      <sha1>b1fsqgejrazrl7d7jayme3dt4ecf85m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Caribbean</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4423028</id>
    <revision>
      <id>923330424</id>
      <parentid>890227634</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-10-27T21:36:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tom.Reding</username>
        <id>9784415</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[MOS:JRSR]]; [[WP:GenFixes]] on; cleanup, [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: Packard’s → Packard's</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="6281" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox automobile
|name=Packard Caribbean
|image=1954 Packard Caribbean.JPG
|caption=1954 Packard Caribbean
|body_style= 2-door [[convertible (car)|convertible]]&lt;br/&gt;2-door [[hardtop]]
|production=1953-1956
|predecessor=[[Packard Super Eight]]
|engine=327CID 4-bbl. L-head "Thunderbolt" 180 hp 8-cylinder (1953) &lt;br/&gt; 352CID Dual 4-bbl. 275 hp V8 (1955) &lt;br/&gt; 374CID Dual 4-bbl. 310 hp V8 (1956) &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Flory Jr.|first=J. "Kelly"|title=American Cars, 1946-1959 Every Model Every Year|year=2008|publisher=McFarland &amp; Company, Inc., Publishers|isbn=978-0-7864-3229-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|wheelbase= {{convert|127|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}
|length= {{convert|218.5|in|mm|0|abbr=on}} &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oldcarbrochures.com/static/NA/Packard/1956%20Packard/1956_Packard_Data_Book/1956%20Packard%20Data%20Book-a05.html |title=Directory Index: Packard/1956 Packard/1956_Packard_Data_Book |publisher=Oldcarbrochures.com |date= |accessdate=2012-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|width = {{convert|78|in|mm|0|abbr=on}} &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oldcarbrochures.com/static/NA/Packard/1955_Packard/1955_Packard_Owners_Manual/1955%20Packard%20Manual-47.html |title=Directory Index: Packard/1955_Packard/1955_Packard_Owners_Manual |publisher=Oldcarbrochures.com |date= |accessdate=2012-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

The '''Packard Caribbean''' was a [[personal luxury car]] produced by the [[Packard|Packard Motor Car Company]] of [[Detroit, Michigan]], during model years 1953 through 1956. Some of the Caribbean's styling was derived from the [[Packard Pan-American|Pan American Packard show car]] of the previous year. It was produced only as a convertible from 1953 to 1955, but a hardtop model was added in its final year of 1956.

==1953==
[[File:Packard Caribbean 1953.jpg|thumb|left|1953 Packard Caribbean Convertible]]
The 1953 '''Caribbean''' was perhaps Packard's most easily identified car because of its full cutout rear wheel housing and side trim, limited to a chrome band outline that stretched the entire length of the car. The band also helped to further delineate the car's wheel openings. A steel continental spare tire was also standard. The hood featured a broad, low leaded-in hood scoop. Bodies for the Caribbean were modified by Mitchell-Bentley Corporation of [[Ionia, Michigan]]. Available "advertised" colors for the car were limited to Polaris Blue, Gulf Green Metallic, Maroon Metallic or Sahara Sand. However, a mere handful of special-ordered cars were built in Ivory or Black.

Interiors of the Caribbean were richly upholstered in leather. Most Caribbeans were also generously optioned, although the [[Ultramatic]] transmission and power windows were optional cost items on the first year model. A total of 750 Caribbeans were built for the first model year, and these cars are highly sought after as collectible cars in the current collectible automobile market. Restored cars regularly sell in the six-figure ranges.

==1954==
[[File:Packard Caribbean 1954 in Belgium 2012.jpg|thumb|left|1954 Packard Caribbean Convertible]]
Beginning in 1954 the Caribbean was elevated to senior Packard status. The Caribbean continued to have its own unique styling features, however the full rear-wheel cut-outs were eliminated and the use of chrome/stainless trim became more liberal, and allowed for two-tone paint combinations. A four-way power seat was available.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Standard Catalog of American Cars 1946-1975|publisher=krause publications|isbn=0-87341-027-0|editor=Gunnell, John A.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Like the [[Packard Patrician|Patrician]], the Caribbean also gained heavier "finned" headlight housings, one of the visual cues applied to help differentiate the senior Packards from their lower priced brethren. The {{convert|359|CID|cc|adj=on}} straight eight senior engine was used in this final incarnation of Packard's straight eight engine. A total of only 400 Caribbeans were produced for the model year, making 1954 the rarest year for the Caribbean.
{{Clear}}

==1955==

[[File:Packard Caribbean 195X.jpg|thumb|left|1955 Packard Caribbean Convertible]]
[[File:Packard Caribbean - Ystad-2018.jpg|thumb|1955 Packard Caribbean Convertible.[[Ystad]] 2018.]]
Model year 1955 saw the Caribbean line, now with V8 engine,  fully adopt the Senior Packard line styling; the car was also available in two or three-tone paint patterns. Designer Richard Teague succeeded in restyling the old Packard Senior body into a sensational, modern-looking design. The single hood scoop was split into two units.  The car also received Packard's torsion level suspension.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oldcarbrochures.com/static/NA/Packard/1955_Packard/1955_Packard_Torsion_Ride_Folder/1955%20Packard%20Torsion%20Ride-02.html |title=Directory Index: Packard/1955_Packard/1955_Packard_Torsion_Ride_Folder |publisher=Oldcarbrochures.com |date= |accessdate=2012-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Production for 1955 stood at 500 units.
{{Clear}}

==1956==
[[File:Packard Caribbean 5588 Convertible 1955.jpg|thumb|left|1956 Packard Caribbean Convertible]]
[[File:1956 Packard Caribbean 1994 Side.jpg|thumb|1956 Packard Caribbean Hardtop]]
For 1956, the Caribbean was broken out into its own luxury series, and gained a hardtop model. Trim differences between the 1955 and 1956 cars were slight. Grille textures changed, and matched the ones used on concurrent Patricians, and the rear treatment, featuring Packard's cathedral style taillights also continued. The headlights also received slightly more exaggerated hoods. Unique new interiors featured reversible seat cushions with cloth on one side and leather on the other. Total model year production equaled 263 hardtops and 276 convertibles. The model was discontinued when Packard production ended in Detroit.

{{Clear}}

==See also==
* [[GAZ-13]], Soviet Chaika

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
* {{cite book | editor = Gunnell, John | title = The Standard Catalog of American Cars 1946-1975 | publisher = Kraus Publications | year = 1987 | isbn = 0-87341-096-3}} &lt;br/&gt;George, Vance- The Packard Club 53-54 Caribbean Roster Keeper

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Caribbean]]
[[Category:Cars introduced in 1953]]
[[Category:1950s cars]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]
[[Category:Personal luxury cars]]</text>
      <sha1>5y8bp5204g3emx7unom3qye1xg4aihj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Cavalier</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4384457</id>
    <revision>
      <id>949604143</id>
      <parentid>865502020</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-04-07T13:16:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iridescent</username>
        <id>937705</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */Cleanup and [[WP:AWB/T|typo fixing]], [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: 2602-2672 → 2602–2672, ’s → 's</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2070" xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Chevrolet Cavalier|AMC Cavalier|Vauxhall Cavalier}}
{{see also|Packard 300}}
[[File:1953 Packard Cavalier 4d sdn - Carolina Cream - fvr.jpg|thumb|1953 Packard Cavalier Touring Sedan model 2602–2672 in ''Carolina Cream'' (26th series)]]
The '''Packard Cavalier ''' is an [[automobile]] produced by the [[Packard|Packard Motor Car Company]] of [[Detroit, Michigan]] during 1953 and 1954.  Produced only as a sedan, the '''Cavalier''' took the place of the [[Packard 300]] model which was fielded in 1951 and 1952 as Packard's mid-range priced vehicle.

The 1953 Cavalier was easily identified from other Packards by its unique chrome side spear trim.

Packard also created a Cavalier sub-series under which three other Packard models, marketed under various names were grouped:
** [[Packard Caribbean]] 2-door [[convertible (car)|convertible]] based on the [[Packard Pan-American]] show car featuring coachwork by Mitchell-Bentley of [[Utica, Michigan]]
** [[Packard Mayfair]] which was based on the two-door Clipper Deluxe, but featuring higher interior luxury through fabrics and chrome trim.

A convertible model, using Cavalier trim, was offered during the 1953 model year and was priced in a more affordable price range than the Caribbean.

For 1954, the Cavalier was again offered as a four-door [[sedan (car)|sedan]] only, but the range also lost its sub series, and the Caribbean was moved into the senior Packard line where it remained until Packard transferred manufacturing to South Bend in 1956.

For the 1955 model year, the Cavalier name was retired and the line was absorbed into the [[Packard Clipper]] Custom series.

==References==

* {{cite book | author = Gunnell, John, Editor | title = The Standard Catalog of American Cars 1946-1975 | publisher = Kraus Publications | year = 1987 | isbn = 0-87341-096-3}}
{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

&lt;!-- Categories --&gt;
[[Category:Packard vehicles|Cavalier]]
[[Category:Cars introduced in 1953]]
[[Category:1950s cars]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]


{{Classicpow-auto-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>6aaogh4sa4o0qx4kka6owi2a9fe1uqj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Clipper</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1533101</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931490710</id>
      <parentid>925752812</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-19T05:16:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelinking 1 books for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.1alpha3</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="45169" xml:space="preserve">{{Original research|date=December 2014}}
{{more footnotes|date=May 2011}}
{{more citations needed|date=November 2011}}
{{overly detailed|date=April 2016}}

{{Infobox automobile
|name= Packard Clipper &lt;br&gt; Clipper (1956 only)
|image= File:1955-Packard-Clipper-Custom-4dr-Sedan.jpg
|caption= 1955 Packard Clipper Custom 4-door Sedan
|assembly = United States&lt;br /&gt;Australia
|body_style= 
|production= 1941–1942&lt;br /&gt;1946–1947&lt;br /&gt;1953–1955&lt;br /&gt;1956 {{small|(Clipper marque)}}&lt;br /&gt;1957
|engine=
|length= 
|width = 
|predecessor=[[Packard 200]]
|related=[[Packard Executive]]&lt;br&gt;[[Packard Panther]]
}}

The '''Packard Clipper''' is an automobile which was built by the [[Packard Motor Car Company]] (and by the later [[Studebaker-Packard Corporation]]) for models years 1941–1942, 1946–1947 and 1953–1957. For 1956 only, Clipper was classified as a stand-alone marque.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Angelo|last=Van Boggart|title=Just Packards|chapter=24|pages=115–117|isbn=1440214271}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Clipper was introduced in April, 1941, as a mid-[[model year]] entry. It was available only as a four-door [[Sedan (automobile)|sedan]]. The Clipper name was reintroduced in 1953, for the automaker's lowest-priced lineup. By 1955, the Clipper models were seen as diluting Packard's marketing as a luxury automobile marque. It was named for a type of sailing ship, called a [[clipper]].

For only the 1956 model year, the '''Clipper''' became a stand-alone make of automobile produced by the [[Studebaker-Packard Corporation]]. The Clipper lineup was aimed at the middle-price field of American automobiles that included [[DeSoto (automobile)|DeSoto]], [[Oldsmobile]], and [[Mercury (automobile)|Mercury]]. Following the closure of Packard's [[Detroit]], [[Michigan]] factory in 1956, the Clipper marque was discontinued, although the Clipper name was applied to 1957 Packards that were built at Studebaker's [[South Bend, Indiana]], factory.

==1941–1947==
{{Tone|section|date=December 2014}}
By the end of the 1930s, Packard president Max M. Gilman realized that his best efforts to improve profitability during the last lean decade had not been enough. The [[Packard One-Twenty]] had arrived in 1935 and saved the company from immediate demise; the [[Packard One-Ten|One-Ten]] had followed, achieving even higher volume. But despite a strong performance in revival year 1937, Packard sales had plummeted as the [[Recession of 1937-1938|depression]] returned in 1938, and the 76,000 sales for the calendar year 1939 were hardly past the break-even point. To be precise, they netted the company a scant half million dollars. This precarious financial state combined with the new model developments among Packard's rivals, GM's [[LaSalle (automobile)|LaSalle]] and the [[Lincoln-Zephyr]], meant that Mr. Gilman needed something radically new, and that he needed it in a hurry if he wanted to save the company.
[[File:1941 Packard Clipper (17265856852).jpg|thumb|1941 the first Clipper]]
[[File:1946 Packard Clipper Six Touring Sedan.jpg|thumb|1946 Packard Clipper Six Touring Sedan]]
[[File:Packard Clipper ca 1947 in Belgium.jpg|thumb|right|1947 Packard Super Clipper Touring Sedan]]
Introduced just eight months before the [[attack on Pearl Harbor]], Packard's hopes for the future rode on the new car design. The Packard Clipper represented a break from traditional styling and embodied an abrupt change in construction techniques. However, [[World War II]] intervened. It made the investment to produce one of the only all-new 1941 American cars impossible to realize in a normal marketplace.

===Initial reception===
The Clipper's market timing could not have been worse. After only 16,600 of the 1941 models were made, and a few thousand 1942s, Detroit stopped building civilian automobiles to concentrate on defense production. By the time cars began rolling off the lines again in late 1945, the still sleek Clipper's impact had been diminished by four years of war. The bright promise of its debut was limited by late introduction; what should have been its solid sophomore year was weakened by [[World War II]]. Its third and fourth years were postponed until 1946–47. Though Packard designer John Reinhart and other Company insiders wanted to retain and "sweeten (in Reinhart's word)" the Clipper's svelte lines, Packard management felt pressured by new postwar designs throughout the industry, introducing the mixed review "bathtub" or "pregnant elephant" 1948–50 Packards.

There were only two other auto makers that introduced all-new 1941 models which were stopped short by the American entry into World War II and thus rendered obsolete before their time. Besides Packard, Ford brought out a much changed design for the 1941 model year — the restyled Ford and its Mercury clone. Nash also produced all-new 1941 models, using monocoque "unitized" construction for the first time. General Motors redesigned for 1942, arguably a piece of bad timing even worse than Packard's, but the 1942 cars were so relatively few in number that they still looked reasonably new when GM resumed automotive production in 1946. The Ford/Mercury comparison is not apt either, primarily because these were quite different cars from Packards, with no pretence of luxury. Nor did their design history mirror the Clipper's. The 1941 Fords and Mercurys were evolutionary developments, clearly related to the 1940s they replaced. The Clipper was such a dramatic break with previous Packard design as to preclude comparisons.

After the war, while Packard opted to improve the Clipper, Ford chose a total restyle for Ford and Mercury in 1949. And, while the bulbous 1941–48 Fords, Mercurys and Nashes were replaced by superior modern designs, the elegant Clipper was replaced by a bulbous 1948 upgrade that, while well received in its initial year, aged quickly in comparison with the new models from the Big 3 and Nash. It is not entirely coincidental that a 1949 [[Mercury Eight]] which had cost $2,000 new was still worth $430 five years later, while a 1949 Packard Eight which had cost $2,200 new was worth only $375. Motor Trend's Tom McCahill, who had raved about the Packard Clipper, called the 1948 Packard "a goat."

The Clipper's timing was unfortunate. The state of the world being beyond Packard's control, Clipper production came to a halt February 9, 1942, just as it was hitting its stride—just as Clipper styling had spread through the entire Packard model lineup.

===Style identity===
A full envelope body of genuinely modern look was a long time coming at the Packard Motor Car Company. [[Cadillac]] was wearing pontoon fenders and flowing lines by 1934, and had adopted all-steel bodies by 1935. In 1936, [[Lincoln (automobile)|Lincoln]] announced the [[Lincoln-Zephyr|Zephyr]], with an all steel unit-body, and a shape so advanced that derivations of it were still in production twelve years later. Chrysler also tried introducing a streamlined platform which the market didn't respond well to, named the [[Chrysler Airflow]]. By comparison, Packard adhered to traditional, crisp, conservative styling. Its main acknowledgement of new-era styling was the skirted fender which appeared in 1933. Packard – like Lincoln and Cadillac – had survived the Depression by building medium-priced cars: the One Twenty, Zephyr and LaSalle, respectively. But unlike its rivals, Packard styling had remained arch-traditional. Unlike Lincoln, Packard followed the medium-priced One-Twenty with an almost-low-priced car, the Six (later briefly known as the One Ten). Unlike Cadillac, Packard refused to market its cheaper models by a different name, and remained wedded to them long after prosperity had returned. By 1941, the year the Clipper debuted, the cheapest Cadillac cost $1,445; the cheapest Packard sold for only $927.

Arguably its conservative design philosophy had stood Packard well in the years leading up to the Clipper. The company was able to advertise—and sold quite a few Packards with—styling continuity from year to year. There was a family resemblance between a 1939, say, and a 1932. In 1939, comparison of its One Twenty with the LaSalle, the company declared that: ''"Packard has style identity...Packard styling is consistent..But look at the 1938 LaSalle! About the only similarity is in the name, and who can be sure that a sudden fanciful style change won't make the 1939 a style orphan?"''

Mercedes-Benz and Rolls-Royce survived for years with very expensive, but dated designs. Packard also survived with limited styling change for at least eight or nine years up through 1940. Still,  Packard hallmarks were very good ones: the chiseled frontispiece; the grille recalling classic Greek architecture; the ox-yoke radiator/hood (or  'bonnet' in the UK) shape harkened back to the Model L of 1904. What's more, the cormorant mascot, red hexagon hubs and arrowhead side-spear, were a combination at least as recognizable and timeless as the stand-up hood ornament and meshwork grille of Mercedes-Benz. Together, these consistent hallmarks unmistakably said "Packard" to school children and bankers alike, and had been the ornamentation of the chosen transport of wealthy Americans since Packard's Boss of the Road Six and Twin Six of the Teens and early Twenties.

To create a modern envelope body while retaining those famous hallmarks was no small undertaking. It is still one of the chief accomplishments of automotive industrial design that the people who created the Packard Clipper were able to do so flawlessly. Advertising invited America to ''"Skipper the Clipper"'' in 1941. It was showing the country an obviously brand-new, up-to-date, in Packard's words, "Windstream" or "Speed-Stream" automobile, yet one which was still undeniably a Packard. Though it did not owe a curve or contour to any previous model, the milestone 1941 Clipper carried the same inimitable radiator and hood shape, as well as the same arrowheads and red hexes, and the same long hood and close-coupled profile of great Packards of the past. The smooth styling transition was a stroke of genius.

When the Clipper debuted in late spring 1941, many thought it more successfully avant garde than the 1936–37 Cord 810/812, more offhandedly elegant than Lincoln's Zephyr, which many wags called a "Ford and a half."

Faced with the same conundrum of appearing modern, an envelope body at odds with a mandatory trademark, a vertical radiator grille, Rolls-Royce could do little better in autumn 1955 than offer a razor-edged 1941 Packard Clipper, albeit with a curved, one-piece windshield, as their new Silver Cloud and concurrent Bentley S-series.

===Design===
Writing in ''The Classic Car'' and ''The Packard Cormorant'', Joel Prescott published an account of the Clipper design which considerably revised the picture offered by George Hamlin and Dwight Heinmuller in ''Packard: A History of the Motor Car and The Company'', published by Automotive Quarterly. The Cormorant has also published excerpts of James A. Ward's book on the decline of the Packard Motor Car Company. The testimony of such designers as [[Howard Darrin]], John Reinhart, William Reithard and Alex Tremulis is on the record.

Prior to World War II, Packard, like most auto companies at the time, did not have a styling department. It was Harley Earl's formidable Art &amp; Colour Section at General Motors that convinced the industry of the importance of styling. But even Earl's efforts did not force rivals to add design departments until after the war.{{clarify|date=November 2011}} A handful of outside consultants, like Raymond Loewy at Studebaker, occasionally sold their designs to American producers. Sometimes the designs even reached production without drastic changes by the body engineers, who at that point largely controlled the shape of cars. One such design consultant was a Californian named Howard "Dutch" Darrin, whose involvement in the Clipper occurred because Packard was his favourite American make.{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}

After returning to America in 1937 following a successful career as a Paris coachbuilder, Darrin looked around for chassis on which to practice his automotive art. He said, "I concentrated on Packards knowing that by lowering the radiator I could make a very beautiful custom-bodied Packard with little change in its basic structure."{{citation needed|date=November 2011}} The result was a long skein of dramatic Packard-Darrins, which were actually catalogued by the company at one point and which led to Darrin's role in the Clipper. "Around 1940, Packard called and asked if I'd design a new standard line car for them. The hitch was that I had only ten days to do so, Chief stylist Ed Macauley (actually vice-president for design) would be on the coast for that amount of time, and if I didn't have anything before he left, it would be a lost cause. The company offered me a thousand dollars a day if I could meet the deadline."

Confident in his ability to put a thousand a day to good use, Darrin said he thought he "could establish enough lines for a full- and quarter-scale model". Later he said that to meet the deadline, he "slept several nights on a drafting table", yet Packard never paid him.{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}

Kaiser-Frazer stylist Bob Robillard admitted that Darrin had held onto his claim as originator of the Clipper almost from the start. He still has copies of a 1946 Darrin paper delivered before the Society of Automotive Engineers, "Does Styling Control the Design of Cars?" In it Darrin states that he widened the Clipper body because the continuous fender-line, which comes right through the door past the A-pillar, required more width for the proper hinging of the door, "the net result being a wider and more roomy car." Reithard disagrees. Before Darrin arrived, he remembered, "the parameters for track, wheelbase and overall length had been established. Other than that we had very little to go on except some very rough sketches and hand-waving from Darrin."

But a quarter century later in Automobile Quarterly, Darrin was still repeating his 1946 claims,{{clarify|date=November 2011}} which were not challenged at the time. As Darrin stated: "Packard introduced the Clipper with a series of ads entitled, 'A Star is Born'", which he considered inaccurate. "The best compliment they paid me was stating that 'three international designers' combined to create the Clipper." Packard was evidently referring to Darrin. George Walker (another outside consultant) and Briggs, all of whom had contributed to the design. But Darrin typically had his own interpretation: "You might construe that to mean that I was the equal of three designers."

While Darrin held himself the central design figure and the original design "called for a sweeping front fender-line that carried right through the doors to the rise of the rear fender, similar to a custom Clipper I built later for Errol Flynn. However, Packard shortened the sweep to fade away at mid-door. This was done as a hedge because no one knew if the through-fender-line would sell." He said Packard Styling also "vandalized the design by throwing on huge gobs of clay along the wheelbase" creating a flare to the lower part of the doors to hide the running boards they added for the same reason. Thus by Darrin's own admission, the Clipper that appeared in production was not entirely his work. Few designers besides Darrin believed this splendid car was the product of ten days' work.

At the time Packard contacted Darrin about designing a production car in the theme of his limited-production Victorias, the Company was, according to Darrin, "....so afraid of GM they couldn't see straight." GM's new C bodies, introduced midway through the 1940 model year, made Packard's traditional bodies, only facelifted since their 1938 introduction, look dated. Packard had, as Darrin said, "....the best chassis in the industry." The upper echelon cars looked more modern than Packard's traditional 1941 bodies.

The Clipper changed that. The only thing hindering the Clipper's ascendency was War II, and after the war, the sheet steel shortages and strikes at vendors that plagued all independents. After the war, for example, Chrysler was held up for weeks just by a strike at the supplier of their door locks. Being a holding company, GM was better able to weather this situation.

Perhaps the best summation of the Clipper's design comes from Joel Prescott: "The truth may well be that the Clipper should be remembered as automotive history's most successful committee design, because assigning the genius of its beautiful lines exclusively to one particular designer cannot now be done with any degree of certainty." And as it turned out, this new look guaranteed the Clipper an appearance never compromised by competitive imitators. In 1942 Cadillac and Buick adopted the same pontoon fender line, but the Clipper still looked unique, apart from and slightly above the crowd, especially the new 1942 senior Clippers, which alone retained the debut 1941's {{convert|127|in|mm|adj=on}} wheelbase, longer hood and front fenders.

===Engineering and evolution===
When considering the great transitional designs that brought us from the art decorations and speed-lining age of the Thirties into the envelope bodies of the Forties, much is always made of Bill Mitchell's famous Cadillac Sixty Special. In particular, its thin window frames, squared-off roof, wider-than-high grille, and concealed running boards were bold steps forward. The Clipper had at least as many pioneering features in an even more integrated package.

The original milestone 1941 Clipper rode the senior wheelbase of {{convert|127|in|mm}} and used the One Twenty's {{convert|282|CID|cc|adj=on}} straight eight, but produced 125&amp;nbsp;bhp (five more than the One Twenty). Despite the familiar engine, few Clipper parts were interchangeable with other models. The chassis was entirely new: a double-drop frame allowed a lower floor without reducing road clearance. The engine was mounted well forward and the rear shocks were angled to assist the traditional Packard fifth shock in controlling side-sway. The front suspension was entirely new, since the lower frame eliminated the need for Packard's traditional long torque arms. A double-link connection between the Pitman arm and steering brackets, with a cross bar and idler arm and two cross tubes, controlled wheel movement.

The 1941 Clipper was the widest production car in the industry and first to be wider than it was tall—a foot wider to be exact. The body from cowl to deck was a single piece of steel—largest in the industry, and the floor pan had only one welded seam from end to end. Single pieces of sheet metal comprised the rear quarters and hood. The hood could be lifted from either side of the car or removed entirely by throwing two levers. Instead of the traditional third side window, ventipanes were incorporated in the rear doors, providing controllable flow-through ventilation. The battery made its first move from under the seat to under the hood, where it stayed warmer and was more accessible. There was a "Ventalarm" whistle to warn when the tank was within a gallon of being full, and an accelerator-activated starter button, so the act of starting simultaneously set the automatic choke. Reithard's beautiful symmetrical dashboard contained a full ration of instruments, including an electric oil pressure gauge adapted from the One Sixty. Options included Packard's Electromatic clutch, which let the driver ignore the clutch pedal in ordinary driving; "Aerodrive" (overdrive); an effective auxiliary under-seat heater, leather upholstery, fender skirts, and, for $275, air conditioning—a Packard first, introduced on all eight-cylinder 1940 models.

Introduced in April 1941, as a single four-door sedan model, the Clipper was by no means a cheap or even medium-priced car. It sold for around $1,400, in a market niche between the One Twenty and One Sixty, competing with the Cadillac Sixty-One, Lincoln Zephyr, Buick Roadmaster and Chrysler New Yorker. Despite a late start, it garnered 16,600 model year sales, almost as many as the One Twenty. Clearly, for Packard, it was the wave of the future. By the 1942 model year, Clipper styling had permeated every Packard in the line, except where special tooling existed—convertibles, taxis, wagons and commercial cars. Curiously, however, the market slot occupied by the 1941 Clipper was abandoned, recreating a gap between the Clipper One Twenty Custom ($1.341) and the Clipper One Sixty ($1,688).

The bulk of the 1942 production was concentrated on the {{convert|120|in|mm|adj=on}} wheelbase junior models, but the One Sixty and One Eighty Clippers proved conclusively that Packard was as much a builder of luxury cars as ever. The 1942 One Sixty sedan, for example, was {{convert|9.5|in|mm}} longer and {{convert|140|lb|kg}} heavier than its square-rigged 1941 predecessor. The One Eighty was wider, almost as long, with more interior width, and with almost as much legroom as the long-wheel-base 1942 One Eighty, which still used the old-style Packard bodywork.

The smooth {{convert|356|CID|cc|adj=on}} straight eight of the One Sixty and One Eighty Clippers, featuring a {{convert|104|lb|kg|adj=on}}, nine-main-bearing crankshaft and hydraulic valve lifters, was the most powerful engine in the industry through 1947, exceeding Cadillac's V8 by {{convert|15|hp}}. It could deliver {{convert|70|mph|km/h}} in second gear overdrive and take the  a {{convert|4000|lb|kg|adj=on}} car to over 100&amp;nbsp;mph on Packard's Proving Grounds banked oval track. In 1950, ten years after Packard's nonpareil nine-main-bearing 356 inline 8 debuted, Rolls-Royce copied the design for their nine-mained, F-head 346-ci B-80 inline 8, used only in a handful of Phantom IVs produced solely for heads of state, military vehicles, and Dennis fire trucks. Like Packard's 245-ci six used in junior Clippers, Packard's 1940–50 356 Super-8 engine was widely used as a marine engine.

The top of the line Clipper One Eighty offered two shades of leather or six colors of wool broadcloth upholstery, Mosstred carpeting from New York's Shulton Looms, walnut grained instrument panels, amboyna burl garnish moldings, seatbacks stuffed with down and rear center armrests. Unlike any other contemporary, the post war Custom Super's headliner was seamed fore to aft instead of sideways. Packard claimed that the unique headliner was adopted "to provide a more spacious feel to the interior."

With a nearly full line of Clippers, Packard managed to build 34,000 1942 models before production ceased in February (an annual rate of around 80,000). According to the late John Reinhart, there is no doubt that Clipper styling would have proliferated in 1943–45. "The next logical step would have been convertibles and commercials—and a wagon." But the war intervened. Whereas Cadillac with its greater facilities was able to field a complete line of restyled 1942s, including convertibles, all of which came right back in 1946, Packard was able only to add a club coupe body before the war.

The club coupe was the sportiest Clipper with about 40 built before production closed down in 1942; a single One Sixty is the only example known to exist. Postwar, about 600 senior coupes were made, compared to about 6,600 senior sedans.

In 1946–47 the numerical designations were dropped and the line consisted of Clipper Sixes and Eights on the {{convert|120|in|mm|adj=on}} wheelbase and Supers and Custom Supers on the {{convert|127|in|mm|adj=on}} wheelbase. For the first time there were now seven-passenger sedans and limousines, riding a {{convert|148|in|mm|adj=on}} wheelbase. For their type, these "professional Packards" enjoyed success. They compare with Cadillac's 1946–47 Seventy-five, beating it not only by {{convert|15|hp}} but by a foot of wheelbase, yet selling for about the same $4,500–$5,000. Counting several thousand bare chassis supplied to commercial body manufacturers, the Seventy-five outsold the long wheelbase Clipper; but for finished cars from the factory, production was about 3,100 cars each for 1946–47 combined.

Many economic experts predicted that the end of World War II would bring a severe recession or perhaps even another depression to the United States. They had history on their side because the US did experience a sharp, albeit brief economic downturn after World War I. Perhaps Packard's management team took these calamitous warnings to heart while planning its postwar strategy. If the economy were to fall, it would make sense to market the low-priced Packards—the Clipper Sixes and Eights—rather than the upmarket Supers and Custom Supers.

The postwar economy proved the experts wrong. It was healthy and many materials, notably sheet steel, were in short supply.{{clarify|date=November 2011}} Workers who would never have struck during the war, now demanded more money, and so the automakers and their suppliers endured a series of costly strikes. These factors, of course, strangled production. At the same time, Americans had money jingling in their pockets, and were willing to spend freely to acquire most anything—especially new cars. Packard could not produce cars in the numbers intended, and it was selling the less profitable junior-series models.

Packard management's chief interest after the war was in the same medium-priced cars that had saved it during the Depression, the Six and junior Eights. The company was still firmly run by President George Christopher, who had helped save it with the One Twenty. Christopher, a graduate of GM's bucket mill B-O-P (Buick-Oldsmobile-Pontiac) divisions, had referred to the luxury Packards as "that goddamn senior stuff." Christopher had junior Clippers in production by October 1945, but it was not until June 1946 that the first Super/Custom Super came down the line. Total Packard production in the first two postwar model years was 82,000, against 91,000 Cadillacs. The difference was that the vast bulk of Packard production was of Clipper Sixes and Eights priced $1,700–2,200. Other than the less popular Series 61 price leader, which replaced the LaSalle for 1941, postwar Cadillacs began around $2,300. Packard could have built and sold as many senior Clippers as Cadillac did Series 62s and 60Specials, had Christopher and his team so chosen.

The long-wheelbase (147-inch) Clipper seven-passenger sedan and limousine were competitive with Cadillac and the low-volume Chrysler Crown Imperial (Lincoln had no long models) in the first two postwar years. Likewise, among owner-driver models, Packard had Cadillac neatly bracketed. The Cadillac Sixty-two sedan and coupe started around $2,300 in 1946—about the same price as the Super Clipper. Against Cadillac's $3,100 Sixty Special, which came only as a four-door sedan, Packard offered the more sumptuously trimmed Custom Super Clipper sedan or coupe for about the same money. The 1946–47 Cadillac Series 62 and 60 Special outsold the concurrent Packard Super and Custom Super Clipper three to one, simply because George Christopher board chose to focus on building junior models, which accounted for 80% of Packard's postwar production.

This is a new point which has been missed in the many postmortems of Packard's fall: Reverting to strictly luxury cars would not have meant downsizing the labor force or contracting the facilities. The market for anything on wheels was bottomless; it did not matter whether the car cost $1,800 (Clipper Eight). $2,300 (Clipper Super) or $2,900 (Custom Super). It would have sold. Nor is this a hindsight judgement, since Packard management was capable of seeing this at the time. At the start of postwar car production, Fortune recorded a consensus that "there now exists a market for from 12 to 14 million cars", and that was in a day when three million or so cars was considered a very good year. "In 1941," Fortune continued, "The 32 million American families owned 29,600,000 cars . . . As 1946 began, the cars were down to 22 million which is not very far from the danger point (18 million) of a transportation breakdown . . . of this remaining total, at least half are in their last days." It did not take a mystic to comprehend these facts, as the late Hickman Price, Jr., who bought Willow Run for the Kaiser-Frazer partners, once said: "I believed we would have a period of three or four years—I remember putting 1950 as the terminal date in which we can sell everything we can make."

Almost immediately after production got rolling in 1945, chief stylist John Reinhart was told, much against his judgment, to update the Clipper. If Dutch Darrin had thought Packard loaded "gobs of clay" onto his original model in 1941, what must he have thought of the hideously bulboid 1948 models? Furthermore, there was no change in market orientation, still rooted firmly in the medium price field. Indeed, in 1948, the final year for President George Christopher, senior Packard production dwindled from 20 percent to 11 percent of total production, trailing Cadillac by tens of thousands. Packard, as a later president, James Nance, stated, "handed the luxury car market to Cadillac on a silver platter."

Professional designers have contemplated continuations of the Clipper into 1948–49, with a broader range of body styles including hardtops and convertibles. Their designs were beautiful and would have kept pace with the all-new Cadillacs and Lincolns of 1949, allowing Packard to come back with its first postwar redesign in 1950. But the key failure was to reorder the corporation's priorities and establish it once again as the American luxury car it had been so successfully for forty years.

Hindsight does suggest that Packard lost its battle for survival at this point, although it would not be evident immediately. Since the company could not achieve GM volume, it would have been smarter to extract more profit from each car it built. Not only were customers standing in line, but by putting top-of-the-line Packards on the road, the public's image of Packard as a luxury car builder would have been enhanced.

The 1948 facelift lost the design continuum the Clipper had offered. Though it retained the Clipper's basic shell, the 1948 model bore no resemblance to its predecessor. The bulbous 1948 design became known to some as the "up-side-down bathtub" or "pregnant elephant" and Packard's market share declined.

The money spent on the facelift, as John Reinhart and others maintained, should have gone into an expansion of Clipper body styles to compete with Cadillac. Packard recognized this too late when it brought out a convertible as the first 1948 body style—a model it should have had by 1947 at the latest. Eighteen months later Cadillac was already out with the Coupe de Ville hardtop, while Packard's newest model was the Station Sedan.

By 1948, it was clear that the future of the car business belonged to the giants. At least one independent manufacturer was ready to make that happen; [[George W. Mason]], President of [[Nash-Kelvinator]]. Mason wanted a postwar combination of independents, a fourth player in an automotive Big Four, with Packard as the luxury division. All independent automakers faced problems. By 1954, there was only a "Big Two," as Chrysler's market share fell to 12.9%.

All Cadillacs had been downsized for 1936, were effectively junior cars ever since, increasingly sharing components with lesser divisions. For example, a 1941 Cadillac convertible shares every piece of sheet metal with the 1941 Pontiac ragtop. Rolls-Royce was principally an aero engine manufacturer since 1935, the cars an increasingly boutique sideline, an "assembled" product cribbing from Buick, Packard, Chrysler, postwar R-Rs and Bentleys having bodies stamped by Pressed Steel near Oxford, who also served much of the rest of British automakers.
 
Despite the company's postwar cash reserves, Packard continued production of its now dated L-head straight eight engines through 1954, competing against a field of OHV V8s. Moreover, the small independent automakers could not achieve unit costs and tool amortization down to GM/Ford levels, nor afford the requisite TV advertising and annual model changes.

==1946–1947==
For 1946–1947 all Packards used Clipper bodies and the "Clipper" name.

==1948–1952==
The Clipper nameplate was dropped for 1948 as Packard issued its Twenty-Second Series automobiles, which, while proclaimed by the company as "all-new," were actually restyled Clippers. Only the 1941–47 Clipper's roof and trunk lid survived. At this time, Packard's president, [[George Christopher]], insisted upon concentrating on sales of the company's lower-priced cars, while longtime competitor Cadillac focused its attentions on the upper end of the market.

The Twenty-Second and Twenty-Third Series (from mid-1949) cars wore the "upside-down bathtub" styling that was briefly in vogue in the late 1940s. Unfortunately for Packard, [[Nash Motors|Nash]], [[Lincoln-Mercury]], and [[Hudson Motor Car Company|Hudson]], the four manufacturers who embraced this type of styling, General Motors introduced designs that were lower-slung, more tightly drawn and less bulbous at around the same time. GM's designs caught the buying public's fancy, while the "bathtubs" quickly fell from favor.

Following a round of bitter corporate infighting in 1949, Packard management finally decided to phase out the "bathtubs" and create the all-new Twenty-Fourth Series for 1951. The new "high-pockets" design (so called because of its high beltline) was much more modern. However, Packard continued to push hard into the lower end of the mid-priced field with its new "200" and "250" models.  While the 250 hardtop and convertible, which would soon be named Mayfair, were an interesting attempt to market upscale coupes which were slightly less bulky than the high line sedans, and were decorated with chrome side scallops reminiscent of the top-shelf 400, the 200 was a full-range, middle-priced line continuing to compete with Oldsmobile, DeSoto, Mercury, the junior Hudsons, and others. [[James J. Nance]] became the company's president in 1952, and he immediately set to work on divorcing the lower-priced cars from the higher-end Packards. To this end, he decreed that the 200 and 200 Deluxe would be consolidated into a new line of Clippers for 1953.

==1953–1956==
[[File:Packard Clipper 4-Door Sedan 1953.jpg|thumb|right|1953 Packard Clipper Sedan]]
[[File:1954 Packard Clipper De Luxe Touring Sedan.jpg|thumb|right|1954 Packard Clipper De Luxe Touring Sedan]]
[[File:Packard Panama Clipper 1955 2.jpg|thumb|right|1955 Packard Panama Clipper]]
[[File:Packard Clipper Super 1955 Heck.jpg|thumb|right|1955 Packard Super Clipper]]

Nance originally had hoped to introduce the new "Clipper" as a stand-alone marque, targeting the mid range price field which he felt was dragging the Packard image down. When word was leaked to the Packard dealer network that they would be losing their best-selling Packard model to "Clipper", they balked. As an appeasement, Nance rolled the Clipper out as a Packard, and worked to transition the cars toward their own make. Thus, the '''Packard Clipper''' name was reintroduced and applied to the company's entry-level models, previously known as the [[Packard 200]], beginning in 1953. Clippers were available in Special and Deluxe trim models, as two- and four-door sedans. A 1953 Clipper went from 0 to 60&amp;nbsp;mph in 17.6 seconds in a Popular Mechanics test.&lt;ref name="books.google.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8NsDAAAAMBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=Popular Mechanics|first=Hearst|last=Magazines|date=1 August 1953|publisher=Hearst Magazines|accessdate=13 January 2019|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; The turning circle was 41&amp;nbsp;ft.&lt;ref name="books.google.com"/&gt;

For 1954, the "Clipper by Packard" was given its own unique rear fender trim and tail lights to further differentiate it from traditional Packards. The cars were also available with a distinctive two-tone paint pattern. For 1955, Packard became a marque in the newly formed [[Studebaker-Packard Corporation]]. The 1955 Clipper Custom offered [[torsion-bar suspension]] something not offered on other models, which only offered [[coil spring|coil]] and [[leaf spring]] suspension. It also had a power steering option. Drivers enjoyed the comfortable ride but complained of door rattles and poor workmanship.&lt;ref&gt;Packard Owners Like Torsion-Bar Ride, ''Popular Mechanics'', September 1955, p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt; Length was 215 15/32 inches long.&lt;ref&gt;http://oldcarbrochures.org/October%202019/1954%20Packard%20Clipper/slides/1954%20Packard%20Clipper-16.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The Packard Clipper Constellation was a two-door hardtop automobile produced by the [[Studebaker-Packard Corporation]] in model years 1955 and 1956. The 1955 model was a [[Packard]] product and sold as part of the Packard Clipper line; for 1956, [[Clipper (automobile)|Clipper]] split from Packard, becoming its own make.

{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Series !! Model !! Model No. !! Body Style !! Price (US$)
|-
| 5540|| Deluxe || 5522|| Touring Sedan || 2,586
|-
| 5540|| Super || 5542|| Touring Sedan || 2,686
|-
| 5540|| Super Panama || 5547|| Hardtop || 2,776
|-
| 5560|| Custom || 5562|| Touring Sedan || 2,926
|-
| 5560|| Custom Constellation || 5567|| Hardtop || 3,076
|-
|}

A total of 8,039 Clipper Deluxe, 14,995 Super and 15,380 Custom was built during model year 1955.
{{Clear}}

==Separate marque: 1956==
[[File:Packard Clipper 4-Door Sedan 1956.jpg|thumb|right|1956 Clipper Super Touring Sedan, model 5642]]
[[File:Packard Clipper Custom 4-Door Sedan 1956.jpg|thumb|right|1956 Clipper Custom Touring Sedan, model 5662]]

Packard's President. James Nance, believed that as a Packard line, the Clipper models were diluting Packard's standing as a luxury automobile marque. For the 1956 model year, the status of being a stand-alone make was emphasized by creating a separate Packard Clipper division within Studebaker-Packard. Clipper's logo was a ship's wheel.

The automaker required Packard-franchised dealers to also execute a separate Clipper Dealer Sales Agreement in order to sell the line. Studebaker agencies in areas not covered by separate Packard dealers were allowed to sign Clipper franchise agreements (and could also take on the regular Packard line as well, subject to factory approval).

Clippers began receiving unique trim and rear quarter panels in 1954, and when Packard introduced its redesigned model in 1955, the Clipper retained its older rear sheet metal while receiving two-tone combinations that were unique to its models. For 1956, the Clipper received new rear sheet metal and tail-light treatments. Clipper marketed two hardtop coupes, the '''Panama''' in the '''Super''' model line and [[Packard Clipper Constellation|Constellation]] in the '''Custom''' range. Both were carry-over model names from the 1955 model year.

Around mid-1955, dealers began complaining that consumers were lukewarm to the cars because they were true Packards and demanded that the Packard name appear somewhere on the cars. Nance refused at first, feeling that placing the Packard name on the cars would undo his plan to save the Packard name for luxury automobiles. However, when dealers began defecting to Mercury franchises, Nance gave in, fearful that the shrinking number of dealers would harm the company more than just the Packard marque. A small "Packard" script emblems began to be placed on the decklids of newly built Clippers. In a complete reversal of Nance's strategy, the emblems were also made available for placement on already-built cars that were languishing on dealers' lots.

By the summer of 1956, Studebaker-Packard was in deep financial trouble. The Packards and Clippers were not selling at anywhere near a profitable level, and the company's creditors refused to advance any further money to the company for new tooling that would have allowed Nance to finally realize his ultimate goal of sharing body components among the company's three lines of cars. In late July, the last Packards and Clippers rolled out of the Conner Avenue factory.

Following the closure of Packard's [[Detroit, Michigan]] factory in 1956, the Clipper marque was discontinued, although the Clipper name was applied to 1957 Packards built at Studebaker's [[South Bend, Indiana]] factory.

===1956 models and production===

* Clipper Deluxe
**4dr Sedan (5,715)
* Clipper Super
**4dr Sedan (5,173)
**2dr Panama hard-top (3,999)
* Clipper Custom
**4dr Sedan (2,219)
**2dr [[Packard Clipper Constellation|Constellation]] hard-top (1,466)
'''Total Clipper production for 1956: 18,572''' (excludes exports, if any)

==Studebaker-Packard: 1957==
[[File:1957 Packard Clipper (5362888340).jpg|thumb|1957 Packard Clipper at a period Auto Show]]
Following the closure of the [[Detroit, Michigan]] Packard plant, Studebaker-Packard entered into a management contract with the [[Curtiss-Wright]] Company. Under C-W's president, Roy T. Hurley, S-P's new president Harold Churchill approved production of a new Packard, to be built in Studebaker's [[South Bend, Indiana]] plant. The new Packards, originally to continue the [[Packard Executive]] nameplate, were to share the [[Studebaker President]] four-door sedan body and new four-door station wagon body as well. The total tooling cost of the new Packard was estimated at roughly $1 million. At some point, however, the Executive name was dropped, as all of the Packards produced for 1957 carried the '''Packard Clipper''' name. Body styles were limited to a four-door "Town Sedan" and the "Country Sedan" station wagon.&lt;ref name="indep"&gt;{{Cite book | title = Standard Catalog of Independents: The Struggle to Survive Among Giants | editor-first = Ron | editor-last = Kowalke | publisher = Krause Publications | ref = Indie | location = Iola, WI | page = [https://archive.org/details/standardcatalogo00ronk/page/270 270] | date = 1999 | isbn = 0-87341-569-8 | url-access = registration | url = https://archive.org/details/standardcatalogo00ronk/page/270 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In order to keep the tooling cost as low as possible, trim components from the 1956 Clippers were used. This was done to make the 1957 model differ in appearance from the President; outside, this included a narrower Packard-style front bumper and 1956 Clipper tail lamps and chromed wheel covers. Other differences include finned rear fenders and differing rear wheel panel treatments, as well as a wide chrome strip across the length of the car (extending across the tailgate on station wagons).&lt;ref name="indep2"&gt;[[#Indie|''Standard Catalog of Independents'']], p. 269&lt;/ref&gt; Inside, the cars' dashboards were fitted with the same basic instrument cluster as used in the previous two years, while trim levels were generally higher than for Studebakers.&lt;ref name="indep2"/&gt;

Sales of the new Clippers were not great; historians differ as to why, although the cars' obvious Studebaker origins (which led the new Clippers to be derisively nicknamed "[[Packardbaker]]s" by many people){{citation needed|date=November 2011}} certainly did not help. Only about 4,800 were sold for the year, of which 869 were station wagons. The only engine option was the [[Supercharger|supercharged]] {{convert|289|CID|cc|abbr=on|adj=on}} Studebaker V8.&lt;ref name="indep"/&gt;

For 1958, the Clipper name was discontinued, and the few Packard automobiles that were produced (four-door sedans, station wagons, and two-door hardtop coupes) were simply known by their marque name. The only exception to this was the [[Packard Hawk]], which was based on the [[Studebaker Golden Hawk]].

==Australian assembly==
The Packard Clipper was assembled in [[Australia]] from [[Knock-down kit|CKD]] kits circa 1955.&lt;ref&gt;The 1955 Packard Clipper, Restored Cars No 46, pages 14-15&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* {{cite book | last = Maloney | first = James H. | title = Studebaker Cars | publisher = Crestline Books | year = 1994 | isbn = 0-87938-884-6 }}
* {{cite book | last = Langworth | first = Richard | title = Studebaker, the Postwar Years | publisher = Motorbooks International | year = 1979 | isbn = 0-87938-058-6}}
* {{cite book | editor-last = Gunnell | editor-first = John | title = The Standard Catalog of American Cars 1946–1975 | publisher = Krause Publications | year = 1987 | isbn = 0-87341-096-3}}
* [http://www.packardinfo.com/index.html Packard Info] - Online library of Packard Information
* Packard Clipper division, Studebaker-Packard Corporation, ''Clipper Dealer Sales Agreement'', Studebaker-Packard Corporation, 1956, company forms 59 and 80-698

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Clipper]]
[[Category:Studebaker vehicles|Packard Clipper]]
[[Category:Cars introduced in 1941]]
[[Category:1950s cars]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]
[[Category:Sedans]]</text>
      <sha1>fy9ircakunydydfst9lfbfz04dcvnyz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Executive</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3699936</id>
    <revision>
      <id>878200149</id>
      <parentid>824587795</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-01-13T17:21:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Robby</username>
        <id>1934512</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* References */ linking to more specific category on Commons</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="5192" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Packard_Executive_Hardtop_Model_5677A.jpg|thumb|right|233px|A Packard Executive Hardtop Model 5677A (1956) in Eastern Switzerland]]
The '''Packard Executive''' was an automobile produced by the [[Packard]]-[[Clipper (automobile)|Clipper]] Division of the [[Studebaker-Packard Corporation]] in 1956.

The Packard Executive was introduced on March 5, 1956 to fill a perceived price gap between the prestige [[Packard]] line and the new Clipper marque, which was in its first year as a separate marque.  In previous years, Clipper models had been Packards.  The most expensive Clipper, the Clipper Custom, listed at $3,065 for the 4-door sedan. The Packard Executive sedan retailed for $3,465, the Executive 2-door coupe $3,560,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Flory | first = J. Kelly | title = American Cars 1946-1959: Every Model Year by Year | year = 2008 | publisher = McFarland | isbn = 978-0-7864-3229-5 | page=761 }}&lt;/ref&gt; while the top-of-the-line Patrician sedan sold for $4,160.

The Executive was marketed with the invitation to “enter the luxury car class now—at a modest investment,” and was aimed at "the young man on the way up."

Effectively, the Packard Executive replaced the entire Clipper Custom line of vehicles, as production of the Customs was ended once the Executive was announced.

The Executive was created by combining the Clipper Custom's body, complete with its distinctive tail light design, and installing the front fenders, hood, and radiator grille assembly of the senior Packard models. It also used the Clipper Custom's {{convert|122|in|mm|adj=on}} wheelbase and its {{convert|352|CID|L|1|abbr=on}} {{convert|275|hp|abbr=on}} overhead valve V8 engine. This contrasted with the engine used by the rest of the 1956 Packard models, which displaced {{convert|374|CID|L|1|abbr=on}} and developed {{convert|295|hp|abbr=on}} ({{convert|310|hp|abbr=on}} for the Caribbean).

Beyond the senior Packard grille and front end sheet metal, Executives were further distinguished from the Clipper line by a unique side trim design that made reference to the senior Packards, and allowed for two-toned paint schemes. However, the interior appointments and instrumentation were pure Clipper. The prototypes produced for the all-new 1957 Packard and Clipper lines show an all-new Executive that would become a baseline Packard. All 1957 Clippers would have an all-new body which shared many inner panels with the all-new large Studebaker. Body panel sharing was the new plan for Studebaker-Packard models. Unfortunately the Insurance Companies would not finance the ambitious plan, and SPC was forced to retrench and ended up sharing body panels with the midsize Studebaker models. There was a 1957 Clipper, the last year to carry that name. Originally, the plan was to call the 1957 model an Executive. It was hoped to be a bridge car until an all-new big Packard could be introduced. See [[Facel-Vega]] for a 1959 proposal for a rebadged Packard.

Executives received their own series designation of 5670. It was offered in two body styles; a two-door hardtop (model 5677), and a four-door Touring Sedan (model 5672).

Although the Executive sold as fast as it was produced,{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} &lt;!--Flory, p.680, says just the opposite.--&gt; it was not enough to substantially improve the financial picture for the Packard-Clipper Division. Even as the Executive was being announced, the media had already been reporting of sales and fiscal woes at the Studebaker-Packard Corporation, and rumors were flying the Packard marque might be discontinued.  These rumors weighed heavily on the company’s efforts to sell any of its products. Buyers did not wish to be stuck with a so-called “orphan” car, where spare parts would no longer be available from a dealer, and resale values would be negatively impacted.

During the Executive's shortened model year of March through June, Packard built a total of 2,779&lt;ref name="Flory, p.761"&gt;Flory, p. 761.&lt;/ref&gt; Executives—1,031 two-door hardtops and 1,748 four-door sedans.&lt;ref name="Flory, p.761"/&gt;

All Detroit production of Packard and Clipper models ceased 25 June 1956 with the shuttering of the Conner Avenue assembly plant. The Packard name was continued for the 1957 and 1958 model years on products based on [[Studebaker]] platforms, built on the same assembly lines in [[South Bend, Indiana]] as the Studebaker models.

== References ==
{{commonscat}}

; Inline
{{reflist}}
; General
* {{cite book | last = Flory | first = J. Kelly | title = American Cars 1946-1959: Every Model Year by Year | year = 2008 | publisher = McFarland | isbn = 978-0-7864-3229-5 }}
* {{cite book | editor-last = Gunnell | editor-first = John | title = The Standard Catalog of American Cars 1946-1975 | publisher = Krause Publications|year = 1987 | isbn = 978-0-87341-096-0 }}
* {{cite book | editor-last = Kimes | editor-first = Beverly Rae | title = Packard: A History of the Motor Car and the Company | publisher = Automobile Quarterly Publications|year = 1978 | isbn = 978-0-915038-11-4 }}

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Executive]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]</text>
      <sha1>kd0p8bgmy93g01l2jxhi92dk45xyvs9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Four Hundred</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4383992</id>
    <revision>
      <id>926089840</id>
      <parentid>926089803</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-14T04:52:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mr.choppers</username>
        <id>8373762</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* 1955 and 1956 */ one more WL won't hurt</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4501" xml:space="preserve">{{about|the hardtop produced from 1955 to 1956|the Packard sedan of the same name|Packard Patrician}}

{{one source|date=April 2019}}
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Packard400.jpg|thumb|275px| Promotional art of the 1955 Packard Four Hundred hard-top coupe]] --&gt;
[[File:Packard 400 1955.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Packard Four Hundred 1955]]
[[File:Packard 400 5580 1955.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Packard Four Hundred 5580 1955]]
[[File:Packard 400 1956.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Packard Four Hundred 1956]]

The '''Packard Four Hundred''' was an automobile built by the [[Studebaker-Packard Corporation]] of [[South Bend, Indiana]] during model years 1955 and 1956.  During its two years in production, the '''Four Hundred''' was built in Packard’s Detroit facilities, and considered part of Packard's senior model range.

Between 1951 and the time the final Detroit-built Packard rolled off the line in 1956, Packard’s marketing strategy and model naming convention was in a constant state of flux as the automaker struggled to redefine itself as a producer of  luxury automobiles, and separate itself from its volume selling Packard models which it designated the [[Packard Clipper]].  As a result, Packard fielded several models which existed for a single year during this period.

In 1951 and 1952 the automaker attempted to use a numeric naming structure that designated Packard’s junior models as [[Packard 200]] and [[Packard 200|Packard 250]] and its senior vehicles as the [[Packard 300]], and bearing the highest trim level available, the [[Packard Patrician|Packard Patrician 400]].  The Patrician 400 replaced the previous model year’s [[Packard Custom 8|Custom 8]] model range.

The '''400''' model name was dropped from the Patrician model range at the beginning of the 1953 model range, however the [[Packard Patrician|Patrician]] name continued to occupy the premium trim level Packard from 1953 through 1956.

==1955 and 1956==

For 1955 the '''Four Hundred''' name was re-employed by Packard and assigned to the automaker's senior model range two-door hardtop. Visual cues that helped to easily identify the 400 included a full color band along the lower portion of the car topped by a partial color band that truncated along the rear edge of the front doors.  "The Four Hundred" in gold anodized script adorned the band between the front wheel well and door edge.

Changes to the 1956 Four Hundred followed those changes to the entire senior Packard line as it attempted to further distance itself from the [[Clipper (automobile)|Clipper]], which was now its own marque in 1956. The Four Hundred shared its body and chassis with the more expensive, new-for-'56 Caribbean hardtop.

Senior Packards received a new grille texture and multi-tone paint schemes. The cars also received an altered headlight housing, with a slightly longer hood stretching over the headlight, as well as a more distinctive egg-crate grille over 1955. All 1956 senior Packards moved the Packard crest to the front of the hood, leaving the "circle-V" emblem in the grille looking somewhat bare.

Power was increased as the new-for-1955 V8 was enlarged from 352 to 374 cubic inches, with a corresponding upgrade in horsepower ratings. A new electronic push-button control for the Ultramatic automatic transmission was offered as an option on the Four Hundred (and Patrician series, standard on Caribbean), the push-buttons located on a pod mounted via a stalk off the steering column. Although sophisticated, it proved troublesome. A simpler column-mounted selector was standard equipment.

In 1956, Studebaker-Packard’s financial position deteriorated to the point where the automaker could no longer afford the luxury of maintaining two distinct makes of cars produced in two distinct facilities. For 1957 Studebaker-Packard fielded a single model range, the [[Packard Clipper|Clipper]]. By the end of the 1958 model year the Packard name ceased as an automotive brand in the United States.

Production totals for 1955 came to 7,206 units for the Packard Four Hundred, and 3,224 units for 1956.

==References==
{{commonscat}}

* {{cite book|editor-last=Gunnell|editor-first=John|title=The Standard Catalog of American Cars 1946-1975|publisher=Krause Publications|year=1987|isbn=978-0-87341-096-0}}

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Four Hundred]]
[[Category:Coupés]]
[[Category:Cars introduced in 1955]]
[[Category:1950s cars]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]</text>
      <sha1>tuyjyje4c0ne8qcw4zy9f7ugg45wxej</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Hawk</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>666617</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931214649</id>
      <parentid>924069473</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-17T17:43:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelinking 1 books for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.1alpha3</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="8510" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox automobile
| name = Packard Hawk
| image = Packard Hawk.jpg
| caption = 
| manufacturer = [[Packard]] ([[Studebaker-Packard Corporation|Studebaker-Packard]])
| aka = 
| production = 
| model_years = 1958
| assembly = [[South Bend, Indiana]], [[United States]]
| designer = 
| body_style = 2-door [[hardtop]]
| layout = [[Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive layout|Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive]]
| platform = 
| related = {{unbulleted list|[[Studebaker Flight Hawk]]|[[Studebaker Golden Hawk]]|[[Studebaker Gran Turismo Hawk]]|[[Studebaker Hawk]]|[[Studebaker Power Hawk]]|[[Studebaker Silver Hawk]]|[[Studebaker Sky Hawk]]}}
| engine = {{convert|289|cuin|L|1|abbr=on}} [[V8 engine|V8]]
| transmission = 3-speed ''Flightomatic'' [[Automatic transmission|automatic]]
| wheelbase = {{convert|120.5|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}
| length = {{convert|205.2|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}
| width = {{convert|71.3|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}
| height = {{convert|54.6|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}
| weight = {{convert|3470|lb|kg|0|abbr=on}}
| predecessor =
| successor =
| sp = us
}}

The '''Packard Hawk''' is a model of automobile. It was the sportiest of the four [[Packard]]-badged [[Studebaker]]s produced in 1958, the final year of Packard production. 

==History and description==
The [[Packard Automotive Plant|Packard Plant]] in [[Detroit]], [[Michigan]] had been leased to [[Curtiss-Wright]] (and would be soon sold to them), and Packard models in this dying-gasp year were all rebadged and retrimmed Studebaker products. The 1958 Packard Hawk was essentially a [[Studebaker Golden Hawk]] 400 with a fiberglass front end and modified deck lid.

Instead of the Studebaker Hawk's upright Mercedes-style grille, the Packard Hawk had a wide, low opening just above the front bumper and covering the whole width of the car.  Above this, a smoothly sloping nose, and hood—reminiscent of the 1953 Studebakers, but with a bulge as on the Golden Hawk—accommodated the engine's [[Paxton Automotive|McCulloch supercharger]] that gave the Studebaker 289 in³ (4.7 L) V8 a total of 275 [[Horsepower#Brake horsepower|bhp]] (205&amp;nbsp;kW).  At the rear, the sides of the fins were coated in metallized [[PET film (biaxially oriented)|PET film]], giving them a shiny metallic gold appearance.  A fake spare-tire bulge adorned the 1953-style Studebaker deck lid.  ''PACKARD'' appeared across the nose, with a gold Packard emblem in script—along with a Hawk badge—on the trunk lid and fins.

The interior was full leather, with full instrumentation in an engine-turned dash.  As on early aircraft and custom boats, padded armrests were mounted outside the windows, a rare touch.

The styling was definitely controversial, often described as 'vacuum-cleaner' or 'catfish' by detractors. The styling has come to be appreciated more today than in its debut.  Only 588 were sold, with Packard's impending demise a likely contributing factor.  Most were equipped with the [[BorgWarner|Borg-Warner]] three-speed automatic transmission.  Approximately 28 were produced with the B-W T85 3-speed w/overdrive manual transmission.  Studebaker-Packard was the first manufacturer to popularize the [[limited slip differential]], which they termed Twin-Traction.  Most Packard Hawks came with TT.  It was certainly the fastest Packard ever sold, since it shared the majority of its components with Studebaker's Golden Hawk.  The price was $3995, about $700 higher than the Studebaker model, but with a more luxurious interior.  Electric window-lifts and power seats were optional extras.

Its rarity and status as the best-regarded of the 'Packardbaker' final-year cars have made the Packard Hawk quite collectible.  Values are roughly double those of the equivalent Studebaker, although they are still low by comparison with Corvettes and Thunderbirds.  Because a Studebaker drivetrain was used, mechanical parts are more readily available, although body and trim parts are more difficult-to-impossible to find.  While it is a unique car, current restoration costs almost always exceed the selling price.

==Specifications==
;Engine
[[File:Packard Hawk rear.jpg|thumb|275px|Rear view]]
*Type: Cast iron 90° V8, Silver Light dish-type pistons
*Displacement: 289 cubic inches
*Bore X stroke: 3.56 X 3.63&amp;nbsp;inches
*Compression ratio: 7.5:1
*Power @ rpm: 275&amp;nbsp;hp (205&amp;nbsp;kW) @ 4,800 rpm
*Torque @ rpm: {{convert|333|lbft|abbr=on}} @ 3,200 rpm
*Valvetrain: In-head valves, solid lifters
*Main bearings: 5
*Ignition: Delco-Remy breaker-point
*Fuel system: 2-bbl Stromberg 380475 downdraft carburetor, McCulloch [[supercharge]]r, {{convert|5|psi|abbr=on}} max
*Lubrication system: Full-pressure, gear-driven
*Electrical system: 12-volt, 30 amperes
*Exhaust system: Cast iron, dual exhaust
&lt;br&gt;
;Transmission
*Type: Borg-Warner Flightomatic automatic
*Ratios
**1st: 2.40:1
**2nd: 1.47:1
**3rd: 1.0:1
**Reverse: 2.0:1

&lt;br&gt;
;Differential
* Type: Semi-floating hypoid, Twin-Traction Spicer-Thornton [[limited slip differential|limited slip]]
* Ratio: 3.31:1
&lt;br&gt;
;Steering
* Type: Power assist, Saginaw recirculating ball
* Ratio: 19.2:1
* Turns, lock-to-lock: 4.5
* Turning circle: {{convert|41|ft|abbr=on}}
&lt;br&gt;
;Brakes
* Type: Four wheel, power-assist Wagner hydraulic
* Front: Cast-iron finned drum, 11 X 2.5 in
* Rear: Cast-iron drum, 10 X 2 in
* Swept area: 172.8 sq in
&lt;br&gt;
;Chassis &amp; Body
[[File:1958 Packard Hawk Convertible.jpg|thumb|275px|1958 Packard Hawk convertible prototype]]
* Construction: All-steel, box section, double-drop side rails, 5 crossmembers
* Body style: Two-door, five passenger hardtop, soft top prototype
* Layout: Front engine, rear-wheel drive
&lt;br&gt;
;Suspension
* Front: Individual unequal-length upper and lower control arms, coil springs, hydraulic shocks, anti-sway bar
* Rear: Live axle, semi-elliptic leaf springs, hydraulic shocks
&lt;br&gt;
;Wheels &amp; Tires
* Wheels: Kelsey-Hays tubeless 5-lug stamped steel
* Front/rear: 5.5 X 14 in 
* Tires: Classic bias-ply
* Front/rear: 8.00 X 14 in
&lt;br&gt;
;Weights &amp; Measures
* Wheelbase: {{convert|120.5|in|cm|abbr=on}}
* Overall length: {{convert|205.2|in|cm|abbr=on}}
* Overall width: {{convert|71.3|in|cm|abbr=on}}
* Overall height: {{convert|54.6|in|cm|abbr=on}}
* Front track: {{convert|56.7|in|cm|abbr=on}}
* Rear track: {{convert|55.7|in|cm|abbr=on}}
* Shipping weight: {{convert|3,470|lb|abbr=on}}
&lt;br&gt;
;Capacities
* Crankcase: {{convert|5|USqt|l|abbr=on}}
* Cooling system: {{convert|17|USqt|l|abbr=on}}
* Fuel tank: {{convert|18|gal|l|abbr=on}}
* Transmission: {{convert|19|USpt|l|abbr=on}}
&lt;br&gt;
;Calculated Data
* Bhp per c.i.d.: 0.95
* Weight per bhp: {{convert|12.62|lb|abbr=on}}
&lt;br&gt;
;Performance
* 0–60&amp;nbsp;mph (96.5 km/h): 12.0 seconds
* ¼ mile ET: 16.7 seconds @ {{convert|82.3|mph|abbr=on}}
* Top speed:  {{convert|125|mph|abbr=on}}
* Fuel mileage: 12 mpg city, 20 mpg highway
&lt;br&gt;
;Production
* 1958 Packard Hawk: 588

==Sources==
* {{cite book| editor-last= Kimes| editor-first= Beverly Rae| title= Packard, a history of the motor car and the company| edition= General |year= 1978| publisher= Automobile Quarterly| isbn= 0-915038-11-0}}
* {{cite book| last= Dawes| first= Nathaniel D.| title= The Packard: 1942–1962| publisher= A.S. Barnes &amp; Co. Inc.|place= Cranbury, New Jersey| year= 1975| isbn= 0-498-01353-7}}
* {{cite book| editor-last= Patrick| editor-first= Mark A. | title= Packard Motor Cars 1946-1958 Photo Archive| publisher=  Iconographix|place= Osceola, Wisconsin| year= 1996| isbn= 1-882256-45-X}}
* {{cite book| last= Clarke| first= R. M.| title= Packard Gold Portfolio 1946–1958| publisher= Motorbooks International| isbn=  1-870642-19-8}}
* {{cite encyclopedia| work= Encyclopedia of American Cars from 1930| title= Packard Hawk| author= Editors of ''Consumer’s Guide''| publisher= Publications International |year= 1993| isbn= 0-7853-0175-5}}
* {{cite book| last= Burness| first= Tad| title= American Car Spotter’s Guide, 1940–65| publisher= Motorbooks International| isbn= 0-87938-057-8| url-access= registration| url= https://archive.org/details/americancarspott0000burn}}

==External links==
{{commonscat|Packard Hawk}}
* [http://www.packardclub.org Packard Automobile Classics, Inc. - The Packard Club]
* [http://packardinfo.com/xoops/html/modules/myalbum/photo.php?lid=9132 Packard Motor Car Information]
* [http://www.packardmuseum.org Homepage of the National Packard Museum]

{{Studebaker-Packard Hawk series}}
{{Packard}}

&lt;!-- Categories --&gt;
[[Category:Packard vehicles|Hawk]]
[[Category:Coupés]]
[[Category:Cars introduced in 1958]]</text>
      <sha1>k3b20g8fsae1c3rlh1ba77s97an6170</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard One-Ten</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4444244</id>
    <revision>
      <id>876226533</id>
      <parentid>876226495</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-12-31T23:51:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Eagleash</username>
        <id>17699731</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:Cars introduced in 1940]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2698" xml:space="preserve">
[[File:1941 Packard 110 Touring Sedan-July 2018 copy.jpg|frameless|right|1941 Packard 110 Touring Sedan owned by Dean Teaster]]
[[Image:1942 Packard 110.JPG|thumb|250px|1942 Packard Model 110 convertible]]
The '''Packard One-Ten ''' (also '''One Ten''' and '''110''') was a range of six-cylinder automobiles produced by the [[Packard|Packard Motor Car Company]] of [[Detroit|Detroit, Michigan]] during the 1940 and 1941 model years.  The One-Ten designation replaced the '''[[Packard Six]]'''.

Packard reintroduced a line of six-cylinder cars in 1937 after a ten-year absence as a response to the economic depression and ongoing recovery cycle in the [[United States]]. As an independent automaker, Packard could not look to other internal divisions to support its luxury models, so the inclusion of the Six, and the later 110, was necessary to aid in supporting the firm's bottom line until better times returned.{{cn|date=October 2018}} 

Critics of the Packard Six and One-Ten have long maintained they hurt Packard's reputation of being America's premier luxury marque.{{cn|date=October 2018}} Still, the reintroduction of the Six could not have come at a better time for the automaker,{{cn|date=October 2018}} just prior to the nation's 1938 economic depression.  By offering the less expensive model, the company was able to attract buyers who would otherwise be unable to purchase more expensive cars.

Built on a shorter wheelbase than the senior Packards, the One-Ten was introduced in August 1939. The One-Ten was available in a broad range of Body styles, including both two and four-door sedans, [[station wagon]] and convertible.  Total output for the 1940 model year was 62,300 units.{{cn|date=October 2018}} 

Following its successful first year, the 1941 One-Ten model range was expanded, and a second trim level, the Deluxe was added. Packard also added a [[Taxicab|taxi]] line within the One-Ten model range. Options for the One-Ten included heater, radio, spotlight, and despite its low-line status, [[air conditioning]].&lt;!--Was a radio even available?--&gt;

For 1942, Packard made a decision to retain numerical designated models within its senior line and the One-Ten reverted to being called Packard Six.

==References==
{{commonscat|Packard 110}}
* {{cite book | author = Kimes, Beverly R., Editor. Clark, Henry A. | title = The Standard Catalog of American Cars 1805-1945 | publisher = Kraus Publications | year = 1996 | isbn = 0-87341-428-4}}

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|One-Ten]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]
[[Category:Sedans]]
[[Category:Convertibles]]
[[Category:Cars introduced in 1940]]


{{Classicprw-auto-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>2x79buyyz22vaniljgwfntkyc199kpv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Panther</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17502096</id>
    <revision>
      <id>917878919</id>
      <parentid>722724347</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-09-25T22:45:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TKOIII</username>
        <id>31772205</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>enlarged image</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2536" xml:space="preserve">{{unreferenced|date=May 2008}}
[[File:Packard - Flickr - Stradablog (2).jpg|thumb|alt=|250x250px]]
The '''Packard Panther''' was a show car, built in 1954 to showcase some of the more radical ideas Packard was considering for its production models in the mid- and late-1950s.

The Panther was a two-seat "personal luxury" sporting [[Convertible (car)|convertible]] (in the same vein as the [[Packard Pan-American|Pan-American]]), with Packard styling cues but much lower stance. A total of four Panthers were built, of which only two survive. Originally, the cars had 1955 [[Packard Clipper|Clipper]] taillights, but these were subsequently removed and replaced with the Senior Series' "cathedral" style units.  The design for the Panther's one-piece fiberglass body is credited to Dick Teague, later of [[American Motors|AMC]], who worked at [[Mitchell-Bentley Corporation]] at the time.  Of the four Panthers built, one was owned by Mitchell-Bentley exec William Mitchell, Sr.&lt;!--Is that the same Mitchell involved with the [[Chevrolet Corvette|Corvette]]?--&gt;  The Mitchell car is the only Panther which had a removable hardtop (which resembled that of the 1955 [[Ford Thunderbird (first generation)|Thunderbird]]). Mitchell sold it in 1988 to the Bortz Collection.  The car was sold in 2006 to an unknown buyer for in excess of $360,000. Although it was shown in late 1954 and 1955 (when Packard was already advertising its new, modern [[overhead valve]] V8), the Panther featured the company's outdated {{convert|327|cid|L|1|abbr=on}} [[Flathead engine|L-head]] (flathead) [[Straight-eight engine|straight-eight]], [[Supercharging|supercharged]] to produce {{convert|275|hp|kW|abbr=on}}, along with [[Ultramatic]] [[automatic transmission]]. Many{{who|date=October 2010}} believe Packard did not want to hurt sales of left-over 1954 L-head models, and by installing the new V8 in the Panther, potential buyers would ignore those cars for the all-new 1955s.

Currently still in existence, the Panther was also named "Daytona", and has been repainted in several different color schemes over the years. Today it remains in excellent condition and is privately owned.

==See also==
* [[Packard Pan-American|Pan-American concept car]]

==External links==
*[http://oldconceptcars.com/1930-2004/packard-panther-daytona-roadster-concept-car-1954/ Packard Panther Daytona Photos], OldConceptCars.com.

{{commonscatinline|Packard Panther Daytona}}
{{Packard}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles]]
[[Category:Concept cars]]

{{Classicpow-auto-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>7bptovg2tw5uex71yl5ojs2xtzg3t2a</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Mayfair</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17502068</id>
    <revision>
      <id>894134263</id>
      <parentid>865502030</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-04-25T21:34:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TKOIII</username>
        <id>31772205</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>moved templates</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1356" xml:space="preserve">[[File:1953 Packard Mayfair 2d htp - Matador Maroon Metallic &amp; Topeka Tan fvrT.jpg|thumb|1953 Packard Mayfair 2-door hardtop]]
The name '''Mayfair'''&lt;ref&gt;Auto Editors of ''Consumer Guide'': ''50 Years of American Automobiles'', p. 313 (New York: Beekman House, 1989. {{ISBN|0-517-68640-6}})&lt;/ref&gt; was applied to the early mid-level hardtop coupes built by the [[Packard|Packard Motor Corporation]] on the 1951-53 Junior body in an attempt to compete in this body style with [[Cadillac]], [[Buick]], and [[Imperial (automobile)|Imperial]] from [[Chrysler]], whose hardtop sales were booming.

Mayfair hardtops were built in the 1951 through 1953 model years.  The Mayfairs were succeeded in 1954 by the [[Packard Pacific|Pacific]], which achieved Senior status with the inclusion of the 359 c.i. engine and full Senior trim.&lt;ref&gt;Langworth, Richard M.: ''Illustrated Packard Buyer's Guide: All Packard Cars and Commercial Vehicles, 1899 to 1958'', pp. 109-113 (Osceola, WI: Motorbooks International, 1991. {{ISBN|0-87938-427-1}})&lt;/ref&gt;

Starting in 1955, Packard renamed its senior hardtop the [[Packard Four Hundred|Four Hundred]].

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

{{-}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Mayfair]]
[[Category:Coupés]]
[[Category:Cars introduced in 1951]]
[[Category:1950s cars]]


{{Classicpow-auto-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>7ihxb7ll066pmrt78clo4iisied4o83</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Light Eight</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24537964</id>
    <revision>
      <id>949308071</id>
      <parentid>865503483</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-04-05T18:58:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mike Peel</username>
        <id>214232</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Changing the Commons category from "Category:Packard vehicles" to "Category:Packard Light Eight"</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="6128" xml:space="preserve">[[File:1932 Packard 900 sedan.JPG|thumb|Packard Light Eight Model 900 4-door sedan (1932)]]

The [[Packard]] Light Eight (series 900) was an automobile model produced by the Packard Motor Car Company of [[Detroit]], [[Michigan]] only during model year 1932. The Light Eight was planned as a new entry model. It competed in the upper middle-class with makes like [[LaSalle (automobile)|LaSalle]], the smaller [[Buick]]s and [[Chrysler]]s, and the top-of-the offerings from [[Studebaker]], [[Hudson Motor Car Company|Hudson]], and [[Nash Motors|Nash]]. The marketing objective was to add a new market segment for Packard during the depression.

Packard did not use yearly model changes in these years. A new series appeared when management felt that there were enough running changes made. Therefore, the Light Eight was introduced during January 1932, together with the new [[V12 engine|V-12]] (called "[[Packard Twin Six|Twin Six]]" in its first year to honor the pioneer Packard model built from 1915 to 1923). [[Packard Standard Eight|Standard Eight]]s and [[Packard Super Eight|Super Eight]]s followed in June 1932.

==Technical==
Construction of the Light Eight followed the Packard tradition. It had a heavy frame with X-bracing, {{convert|8|in|mm|0|adj=on}} deep side members,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oldcarbrochures.com/static/NA/Packard/1932_Packard/1932_Packard_Light_Eight_Data_Book/1932%20Packard%20Data%20Book-44-45.html |title=1932 Packard Light Eight Data Book |pages=44–45 |publisher=Oldcarbrochures.com |date= |accessdate=2012-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the usual rear-wheel drive. Wheelbase was {{convert|127.75|in|mm|0|}}. Power came from a {{convert|320|CID|L|1|abbr=on}} straight eight engine with a compression ratio of 6:0, delivering {{convert|110|hp|kW PS|0|abbr=on}}. It had a vacuum-plate clutch and an angle set hypoid differential. Battery and toolboxes were mounted on the fenders. Full instrumentation was used.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oldcarbrochures.com/static/NA/Packard/1932_Packard/1932_Packard_Light_Eight_Data_Book/1932%20Packard%20Data%20Book-46-47.html |title=1932 Packard Light Eight Data Book |pages=46–47 |publisher=Oldcarbrochures.com |date= |accessdate=2012-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The car was distinguished by a grille that had the traditional ox-yoke shape, but also with a then fashionable "shovel" nose. Closed Light Eights had a quarter window layout that was not shared by other Packards.

The Light Eight used the same engine as the Standard Eight, but was lighter - {{convert|4115|lb|kg|0|abbr=on}} for the sedan vs. {{convert|4570|lb|kg|0|abbr=on}} for the model 901 Standard Eight sedan. It was also a good performer for its day.

==Body styles==
The Light Eight series 900 was available in four body styles:

Style # 553 4-door, 5-passenger Sedan&lt;br /&gt;
Style # 558 2-door, 2/4-passenger Stationary (rumble seat) Coupe&lt;br /&gt;
Style # 559 2-door, 2/4-passenger (rumble seat) Roadster Coupe&lt;br /&gt;
Style # 563 2-door, 5-passenger Sedan Coupe (sometimes referred as a "Victoria" Coupe)

==Prices and options==
[[File:1932 Packard 904 Deluxe 8 Coupe (21736590312).jpg|thumb|left|1932 Packard 904 Deluxe 8 Coupe]]
A Light Eight 4-door, 5-passenger Sedan was priced at USD $1,750, compared to $2,485 for a similar Standard Eight Sedan. The three other Light Eight body styles cost $1,795 each. Packard managed to sell 6,785 units of its new model. In comparison, 7,669 units of the Standard Eight were sold during the shorter model run, from 23 June 1932, until 5 January 1933. The automaker had lower profits from the Light Eight compared with the Standard Eight.

Options for the Light Eight included Dual sided or rear-mounted spare wheels, sidemount cover(s), cigar lighter, a right-hand tail-light, luggage rack, full rear bumper, and fender park lights, the latter was priced at $65.00.

==Market position==
The Light Eight was intended as Packard's price leader at the entry level of the luxury car market. It was attractive to buyers, but it failed its main reason for existence, which was to lure away buyers from its rivals. Instead, it hurt sales of Packard's volume line, the Standard Eight. Amidst the Great Depression, many prospects for a Standard Eight ended buying a Light Eight. Although it offered not as much luxury, it had many features found in Packard's bigger model. It was powered by the same {{convert|110|hp|kW|0|abbr=on}} engine as the Standard Eight; it had a wheelbase that was only {{convert|1.75|in|mm|0|adj=on}} shorter - and its lower weight brought more performance. The Light Eight included Packard prestige at a much lower price.

Packard learned its lesson quickly. There was no Light Eight for its 10th series (1933) line. It renamed the Standard Eight as simply the [[Packard Eight|Eight]] and integrated a four-model subseries that was patterned after the Light Eight. Although the shovel nose was gone, the quarter window treatment remained, and the differential that was introduced with the Light Eight was now found in all Eights. This 1001 series was no longer available at low prices: they started at $2,150 for the sedan and went up to $2,250 for the roadster.

The Light Eight brought the experience to Packard to build and market an upper middle-class model. In this sense, it is the predecessor for the automaker's second try into this market segment, the [[Packard One-Twenty]], that was introduced in 1935.

==Sources==
{{reflist}}
* Kimes, Beverly Rae, editor: ''Packard: A History of the Motor Car and the Company''. Automobile Quarterly Publications, {{ISBN|0-915038-11-0}}
* Kimes, Beverly R. (editor), Clark, Henry A.: ''The Standard Catalog of American Cars 1805–1945''. Krause Publications (1985), {{ISBN|0-87341-045-9}}

== External links ==
{{commonscat|Packard Light Eight}}
* [http://www.packardclub.org The Packard Club] (go to "encyclopedia" and then click 1932 button)
* [http://packardinfo.com/xoops/html/modules/modelinfo/index.php?mode=year&amp;id=1932&amp;ButtonYear=Go Packard Information] on 1932 Light Eight

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Light Eight]]
[[Category:1930s cars]]</text>
      <sha1>g5qj2puynv0n84ak8r8242abe1ljo2h</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>1957 and 1958 Packards</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>669454</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941403560</id>
      <parentid>908802522</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-18T11:08:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2A02:C7D:3FB0:300:9803:2801:14A4:C90E</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Trivia */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="6118" xml:space="preserve">{{Notability|date=November 2018}}{{No citations|date=November 2018}}

The '''1957''' and '''1958''' '''Packard''' lineup of [[automobiles]] were based on [[Studebaker]] models: restyled, rebadged, and given more luxurious interiors.  After 1956 production, the [[Packard]] engine and transmission factory was leased to the [[Curtiss-Wright]] Corporation while the assembly plant on [[Detroit, Michigan|Detroit]]'s East Grand Boulevard was sold, ending the line of Packard-built cars.  However, Studebaker-Packard executives hoped to keep the Packard name alive until a fully restyled model could be funded, developed, and produced.  These cars were built in hopes that enough would be sold to enable the company to design and build a completely new luxury Packard.

==1957 Packard Clipper==
For the 1957 model year, Studebaker-Packard took its top-of-the-line model, the [[Studebaker President|President]], and added a revised grille and taillights along with a Packard-styled dashboard and called the car the '''[[Packard Clipper]]'''.  Two models were produced in 1957, a four-door '''Town Sedan''' and a station wagon '''Clipper Country Sedan'''.

Carryover parts from earlier Packard models included taillights, wheel covers, block letters on hood, instruments and radios. The headlight 'eyebrows' and front bumper assembly were styled for a Packard appearance. A 1955 hood ornament was modified to fit the Studebaker hood shape and the long, wide side trim was designed to be reminiscent of recent Packard trim. A stamped overlay for the lower rear fenders also gave them a body crease line suggestive of the side trim of the 1956 Caribbean.

Dashboard and interior were all Packard styled. Some former President features like the rear folding seat armrest and faired-in door armrests were reserved for the Clippers, with the addition of door mounted ashtrays, thick pile carpeting, and exclusive Packard-style cloth/vinyl fabrics. Other unique features included under-dash courtesy lights, fully padded dash top (that unfortunately didn't hold up well long term in the sun), padded sun visors, and gold-plated horn ring.

When Packard dealers saw the resulting car at regional previews, the response was quick, angry, and loud.  Many dealers felt the Clipper was too similar to the Studebaker on which it was based and dropped Packard completely.  Sales were a low 4,809, almost all of which were the Town Sedan.  Critics bestowed the derisive name "[[Packardbaker]]" on the cars.

In order to produce an engine of appropriate power for a Packard, a McCulloch-[[supercharger|supercharged]] version of Studebaker's 289 in³ (4.7 L) [[small-block V8|small-block]] [[V8 engine|V8]] was used, giving 275&amp;nbsp;bhp (205&amp;nbsp;kW), equivalent to the Packard engines in use the year before (and likewise used in the [[Studebaker Golden Hawk]]).  Since the Studebaker-bodied cars were quite a bit lighter than the previous year's Packards, the 1957 Packard range actually had quite exceptional performance for the time.

Writer and auto historian Richard Langworth has noted that while these cars weren't truly Packards, they were, however, very good Studebakers.

==Final Packards==
[[Image:1958 Packard.jpg|thumb|275px|1958 Packard 2-door hardtop coupe]]
1958 saw the Packard line expanded to four models; a 4-door sedan, a 2-door hardtop (sometimes referred to as the "Starlight", a name used by Studebaker), a 4-door station wagon, and the Packard Hawk, a modification of Studebaker's [[Studebaker Golden Hawk|Golden Hawk]] with a "fishmouth" Packard grille.

Restyled by Duncan McRae, Studebaker-Packard's finances dictated that the changes for 1958 be made as cheaply as possible.  Quad headlights, as on Studebakers, were achieved by affixing pods to the previous year's front fenders designed for two headlights. In the rear, McRae attempted to follow the tailfin craze established by Chrysler's 1957 "Forward Look" by crafting outward-canted steel fin extensions that were mounted to the tops of the existing vertical rear fenders.  1956 Clipper taillight units continued to be used.  Packards also adopted a low, wide "fishmouth" grille to further distinguish them from their Studebaker cousins. Other notable changes included the hardtops' astonishingly attractive rooflines, very similar to concurrent Chrysler/Desoto designs. Also, the switch to a one-piece drive shaft allowed Studebaker engineers to flatten the floor, which also allowed flattening of the roof panels on sedan and hardtop models. Packard (and Studebaker) also switched to 14" wheels so most 1958 models are noticeably lower.

[[Image:1958 Packard rear.jpg|thumb|250px|1958 Packard's grafted tailfins on 1956 Clipper taillights.]]
Despite McRae's efforts, the car that emerged appeared cobbled together, rather than as a cohesive design. Auto reviewer "Uncle" Tom McCahill remarked that from the rear it looked as if the cars had been left in the sun too long and the canted fiberglass fins had started to melt down the straight rear fender sides.

Only 2,034 of the three standard models (sedan, hardtop and station wagon) were produced; an additional 588 Packard Hawks were built as well.  The rarest of all '58 Packards is the [[station wagon]], with only 159 produced.  The last Packard rolled off the [[South Bend, Indiana|South Bend]] assembly line on July 25, 1958.

In 1962 the Studebaker-Packard Corporation officially dropped "Packard" from its name.

==Trivia==

A pink, purple, and gold 1958 Packard estate car is seen in the 2001 film ''[[Hearts in Atlantis (film)|Hearts in Atlantis]]''.

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==Further reading==
* {{cite book | editor = Gunnell, John | title = The Standard Catalog of American Cars 1946-1975 | publisher = Kraus Publications | year = 1987 | isbn = 0-87341-096-3}}
* Langworth, Richard. 1957-58 ''"Packardbaker": America's First Replicar.'' pp.&amp;nbsp;8–20, '''Collectible Automobile Magazine''' April 1985, Vol.5, Number 6.

{{Packard}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:1957 And 1958 Packards}}
[[Category:Packard vehicles]]
[[Category:Studebaker vehicles|Clipper]]
[[Category:Station wagons|Packard]]</text>
      <sha1>m7hbcp5jrzoxa4ts4ym1v8ff5t3cbg1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Pan-American</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26158724</id>
    <revision>
      <id>945087775</id>
      <parentid>919589290</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-11T18:59:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CommonsDelinker</username>
        <id>2304267</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Removing [[:c:File:PackardPanAmerican.jpg|PackardPanAmerican.jpg]], it has been deleted from Commons by [[:c:User:Green Giant|Green Giant]] because: per [[:c:Commons:Deletion requests/Files uploaded by TKOIII|]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2357" xml:space="preserve">The '''Packard Pan-American ''' is a [[concept car]] produced for the [[Packard|Packard Motor Car Company]] of [[Detroit]], [[Michigan]] in 1952.

Conceived as a moderate-performance two-seater by [[Hugh Ferry]], president of Packard, it was built by [[Henney Body Company|Henney]], which was responsible for fitting custom [[hearse]] and [[ambulance]] bodies on Packard chassis.&lt;ref name='Flory1022'&gt;Flory, J. "Kelly", Jr. "Packard Pan-American", in ''American Cars 1946-1959'' (Jefferson, NC:  McFarland &amp; Coy, 2008), p.1022.&lt;/ref&gt; A status symbol for a carmaker at the time, this sort of car was a very unlikely project for Packard.&lt;ref name='Flory1022'/&gt;

With styling by Henney, it was based on the 1951 [[Packard 200|Series 250]] convertible,&lt;!--including the {{convert|327|cid|l|1|abbr=on}} L8?--&gt; and ready in time for the 1952 [[New York International Motor Sports Show]].&lt;ref&gt;Flory, p.1022.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Chopped and channeled#Sectioning|Sectioned]] and [[Chopped and channeled#Channeling|channelled]], in a fashion reminiscent of the [[Buick Skylark|1953 Skylark]], and wearing the trademark Packard grille, it "was elegantly trimmed throughout".&lt;ref name='Flory1022'/&gt;

Packard spent [[United States dollar|US$]]10,000 building the Pan-American, and management tried in vain to imagine, let alone develop, a market for a roadster projected to cost at least US$18,000,&lt;ref name='Flory1022'/&gt; at a time when the top-line [[Lincoln Capri]] six-passenger convertible went for US$3,665,&lt;ref&gt;Flory, p.440.&lt;/ref&gt; the premier eight-place [[Cadillac Series 70#1950–1953|Cadillac Series 75 Fleetwood]] US$5643,&lt;ref name="Flory, p.456"&gt;Flory, p.456.&lt;/ref&gt; and even Packard's [[Packard Patrician|Patrician 400]], their most expensive production model, was only US$3,767, and a six-seater.&lt;ref name="Flory, p.456"/&gt;

As many as six examples were built. The Pan-American did inspire a successful six-place model, the [[Packard Cavalier|Cavalier]], which debuted in 1953.&lt;ref name='Flory1022'/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Packard Panther|Panther concept car]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
* Flory, J. "Kelly", Jr. "Packard Pan-American", in ''American Cars 1946-1959'', p.&amp;nbsp;1022. Jefferson, NC:  McFarland &amp; Coy, 2008.

{{Packard}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Pan-American]]
[[Category:1950s cars]]
[[Category:Cars introduced in 1952]]
[[Category:Concept cars]]</text>
      <sha1>ohd8kgghmwp9fk1v7dgybrw7pbamwvu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Model 30</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26713647</id>
    <revision>
      <id>824587820</id>
      <parentid>816797918</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-02-08T07:26:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>I dream of horses</username>
        <id>9676078</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[WP:WCW|Checking Wikipedia for error]]s using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1606" xml:space="preserve">{{see also|Packard Model 30 (series U)}}

{{Infobox automobile
| name           = Packard Model 30 
| image          = 
| manufacturer   = Packard Motor Car Company
| aka            = 
| production     = 
| assembly       = [[Packard Automotive Plant]], [[Detroit, MI]]
| predecessor    = [[Packard Model G]]
| successor      = [[Packard Twin Six]]
| class          = 
| body_style     = 
| layout         = [[Front-engine, rear-wheel drive layout|Front-engine, rear-wheel drive]]
| platform       = 
| engine         = 432 cubic inch [[T-head engine]]
| transmission   = 
| wheelbase      = 123.5 inches
| length         = 
| width          = 
| height         = 
| weight         = 
| related        = 
| designer       = 
| sp             = 
}}

The '''[[Packard]] Model 30''' was a luxury car introduced for the 1907 model year. It replaced the Model S. It featured a touring body with [[right hand drive]] and a crank starter mounted to a four-cylinder [[T-head engine]]. The pricey 30 was marketed just above the Model 18 (literally a 9/10 scale model of the '''Model 30'''). In 1911 Packard introduced the [[Packard Six]] as a 1912 model and phased out the four-cylinder '''Model 30'''s.&lt;ref&gt;Hemmings Classic Car Volume 6, Issue 5 February 2010 page 22-25&lt;/ref&gt; The Model 30 was replaced by the [[Packard Twin Six]] as the top level car in May 1915.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ateupwithmotor.com/model-histories/packard-twelve-twin-six-history/] History of Packard Twin Six&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Model 30]]


{{Veteran-auto-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>0acqognz1kna0w9ftzi30mrvp486vug</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard 300</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4406957</id>
    <revision>
      <id>878199807</id>
      <parentid>865502011</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-01-13T17:18:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Robby</username>
        <id>1934512</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Sources */ link to more specific category on commons</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2415" xml:space="preserve">[[File:1952 Packard 300 (5019099916).jpg|right|thumb|A 1952 Packard 300.]]
The '''Packard 300''' was an automobile built and sold by the [[Packard|Packard Motor Car Company]] of Detroit, Michigan for model years 1951 and 1952.  The '''300''' represented the upper mid-range Packard model and provided better appointments than the [[Packard 200]] or the Packard 250 models.  The premier Packard offered during these years was the [[Packard Patrician|Packard Patrician 400]].

For both model years the 300 model was built as a four-door sedan only and was mounted on Packard's {{convert|127|in|mm|adj=on}} wheelbase.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oldcarbrochures.com/static/NA/Packard/1953%20Packard/1953_Packard_Owners_Manual/1953%20Packard%20Manual-47.html |title=Directory Index: Packard/1953 Packard/1953_Packard_Owners_Manual |publisher=Oldcarbrochures.com |date= |accessdate=2012-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; The car included the basic trim appointments found in the 200 and 200 Deluxe model lines and included tinted windows, a robe rail for backseat passengers and striped interior fabrics. Exterior trim included full wheel covers as well as Packard's graceful pelican hood ornament. The 300 also received a wrap around rear window which it shared with the Patrician models.

Power for the car in both years came from Packard's venerable Super Eight engine, the {{convert|327|CID|cc|adj=on}} "Thunderbolt" inline eight which was shared with the 250 line.  A three-speed manual shift was standard while Packard's [[Ultramatic]] automatic transmission was offered as optional equipment.

In 1953 the 300 was renamed the [[Packard Cavalier]] as Packard moved away from its strict numeric model naming structure.  A total of 22,309 Packard 300s were built in the model's two years on the market with 1951's total of 15,309 representing the high sales mark for the 300 model.

==Sources==
{{commonscat}}
{{reflist}}
* {{cite book | author = Gunnell, John, Editor | title = The Standard Catalog of American Cars 1946-1975 | publisher = Krause Publications | year = 1987 | isbn = 0-87341-096-3}}
* {{cite book | author = Dawes, Nathaniel D. | title = The Packard: 1942-1962 | publisher = A.S. Barnes &amp; Co. Inc., Cranbury NJ | year = 1975 | isbn = 0-498-01353-7}}

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|300]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]
[[Category:1950s cars]]


{{Classicpow-auto-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>dgvpxemftyyfd38xmc05kyp3ciqmbia</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Single-Cylinder</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33305159</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943558747</id>
      <parentid>934400046</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-02T15:26:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>John of Reading</username>
        <id>11308236</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[WP:AWB/GF|General]] fixes, removed the redundant "See also" heading</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="3376" xml:space="preserve">The '''Packard Single-Cylinder''' cars are a group of cars made by the [[Packard]] automobile company from 1899-1903. The four cylinder [[Packard Model G]] was introduced in 1904.

== Models ==
[[File:Packard Model A.jpg|thumb|Model A Packard]]
'''Model A(1899)''': The Model A was the first automobile produced by the Packard Motor Company.  Only five were made. The last one produced was also the first Packard sold, to a Warren, Ohio, business man named George Kirkham.&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;{{cite book|last=Kimes|first=Beverly|title=standard catalog of American Cars 1805-1942|year=1996|publisher=Krause publications|isbn=0-87341-428-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Model !! Engine !! HP !! Transmission !! Wheelbase
|-
| A || 142.6CID cast-iron block one-cylinder|| 9 || 2-speed [[Epicyclic gearing|planetary]] || 71.5"
|}

'''Model B(1900–1901)''': The Model B was the second model produced by Packard.  Steering was still by a lever, but a [[Automobile pedal|foot pedal]] was now used for speed control rather than a lever like in the Model A.&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt;
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Model!! Engine !! HP !! Transmission !! Wheelbase
|-
| B || 142.6CID cast iron block one cylinder || 9&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://packardinfo.com/xoops/html/modules/modelinfo/viewmodel.php?model=220|title=Packard Motor Car Information - Packard Model Info|website=packardinfo.com|accessdate=13 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; || 2-speed planetary || 76"
|}

'''Model C(1901)''': The Model C was the third model produced by Packard. It was one step up from the Model B with a more powerful engine. It was also the first Packard to use a [[steering wheel]] instead of a [[tiller]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.conceptcarz.com/vehicle/z11535/packard-model-c.aspx|title=1901 Packard Model C History, Pictures, Value, Auction Sales, Research and News|website=conceptcarz.com|accessdate=13 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Top speed was {{convert|25|mi/h|km/h|abbr=on}}.
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Model!! Engine !! HP !! Transmission !! Wheelbase
|-
| C || 183.8CID cast iron block one cylinder.&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt; || 12 || 2-speed planetary || 76"
|}

'''Model F (1901–1903)''': The Packard Model F was the last single-cylinder car made by the Packard Motor Company. It had some major advances, including a new 3-speed transmission. When it competed in an economy contest, the Model F averaged {{convert|27.5|mpgus|L/100 km mpgimp|abbr=on}} [[Fuel economy in automobiles|mpg]].&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt; It was the most expensive Packard till then, costing $2,500 in 1902(the price was lowered to $2,300 in 1903&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt;). It was replaced by the [[Packard Model G|Model G]].
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Model!! Engine !! HP !! Transmission !! Wheelbase
|-
| F || 183.8CID cast iron block one cylinder.&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt; || 12 || 3-speed sliding gear || 84"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://packardinfo.com/xoops/html/modules/modelinfo/viewmodel.php?model=223|title=Packard Motor Car Information - Packard Model Info|website=packardinfo.com|accessdate=13 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [https://www.wired.com/2016/05/tale-epic-coast-coast-road-trip-1903/ 1903 Transcontinental Tour in a Packard F]

{{commons category|Packard vehicles}}
{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:First car made by manufacturer]]
[[Category:Packard vehicles|Single cylinder]]</text>
      <sha1>o2qmvfnmtq69iatwd8dvth4n0qiqutg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Eight</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>40554417</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937012666</id>
      <parentid>937012434</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-22T11:42:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Regushee</username>
        <id>4779744</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12069" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox automobile
| image = File:'30 Packard Deluxe Eight Roadster (MIAS '10).jpg
| caption = 1930 De Luxe Eight [[Roadster (automobile)|Roadster]]
| name = Packard Eight
| manufacturer=[[Packard]]
| production=1930-35
| model_years=
| assembly=[[Packard Automotive Plant]], [[Detroit, MI]]
| predecessor=[[Packard Six]]
| successor=[[Packard 180]]
| class=[[Luxury car]]
| body_style=•2-door [[Roadster (automobile)|roadster]]&lt;br/&gt;•2-door [[coupé]]&lt;br/&gt;•2-door [[convertible]] [[Victoria (bodystyle)|Victoria]]&lt;br/&gt;•4-door [[Sedan (automobile)|sedan]]&lt;br/&gt;•4-door [[Phaeton body|phaeton]]&lt;br/&gt;•4-door dual-cowl phaeton &amp;  Sport Phaeton&lt;br/&gt;•[[town car]]&lt;br/&gt;•[[Landau (automobile)|landau]]
| layout=[[Front-engine, rear-wheel drive layout|Front engine, rear drive]]
| related=[[Packard Light Eight|Light Eight]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Packard 120|120]]
}}

The '''Packard Eight''' was a [[luxury automobile]] produced by [[Packard]] between 1930 and 1938, and was a progression from the earlier [[Packard Six]] which was first introduced in 1913.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1938/1938%20Packard%20Ad-01.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 19 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

Offered in four models, the '''Standard Eight''', '''Custom Eight''', &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1931/1931%20Packard%20Ad-02.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;, '''De Luxe Eight''',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1930/1930%20Packard%20Ad-05.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;  and '''Speedster''' it was powered by a low-compression aluminum-head&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-01.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Flathead engine|L-head]] [[Straight-eight engine|inline eight]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1935/1935%20Packard%20Ad-01.jpg Old Car Advertising] Retrieved 12 September 2013&lt;/ref&gt; producing {{convert|90|bhp|kW|0|abbr=on}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1930/1930%20Packard%20Ad-08.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; (hence the name).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-01.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013. The same engine would be used in the [[Packard 120|120]], &amp; remained in production until 1955.&lt;/ref&gt; Packard ads bragged the engine "floated" on new rubber mounts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-08.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; Power would be upgraded to {{convert|110|hp|kW|abbr=on}} in 1932&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-09.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; and {{convert|120|hp|kW|abbr=on}} in 1933.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1933/1933%20Packard%20Ad-01.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Eight offered optional (no extra cost)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-10.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; four-speed [[synchromesh]] [[Transmission (mechanics)|transmission]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1931/1931%20Packard%20Ad-06.jpg Old Car Advertising]; [http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-01.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; Like other Packards of this era, it featured Ride Control, a system of dash-adjustable hydraulic [[shock absorber]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-01.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Eight also featured automatic chassis lubrication&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1931/1931%20Packard%20Ad-06.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; and "shatterproof" glass.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1930/1930%20Packard%20Ad-03.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Eight was available on several [[wheelbase]]s:  {{convert|127.5|in|mm|abbr=on}} and {{convert|134.5|in|mm|abbr=on}} for the 1930 Standard Eight,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1930/1930%20Packard%20Ad-08.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; {{convert|140|in|mm|abbr=on}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1931/1931%20Packard%20Ad-10.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; and {{convert|145.5|in|mm|abbr=on}} for the De Luxe in 1931,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1930/1930%20Packard%20Ad-06.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;  {{convert|130|in|mm|abbr=on}} and {{convert|137|in|mm|abbr=on}} for the 1932 Standard Eight.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-10.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; For 1938, the Eight's wheelbase was stretched {{convert|7|in|mm|abbr=on}} over 1937, and the body was also wider.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1938/1938%20Packard%20Ad-06.html Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 5 October 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!--1938's 8, ex-120, was {{convert|127|in|mm|abbr=on}}, up {{convert|7|in|mm|abbr=on}} over 1937.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1938/1938%20Packard%20Ad-07.html Old Car Advertising] and [http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1938/1938%20Packard%20Ad-06.html Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 5 October 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

It was advertised  as a two-door [[Roadster (automobile)|roadster]], two-door [[convertible]] &amp; two-door [[convertible]] [[Victoria (bodystyle)|Victoria]] (both new for 1932),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-04.jpg Old Car Advertising]; [http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-03.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Phaeton body|phaeton]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1930/1930%20Packard%20Ad-10.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; four-door dual-cowl phaeton&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1930/1930%20Packard%20Ad-10.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; &amp; Sport Phaeton (a four-door four-seat dual-cowl phaeton new in 1932)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-02.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; two-door [[coupé]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1930/1930%20Packard%20Ad-11.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; four-door [[Sedan (automobile)|sedan]], [[Landau (automobile)|landau]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1930/1930%20Packard%20Ad-02.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; [[town car]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1930/1930%20Packard%20Ad-15.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[limousine]]. The Packard eight utilized a very rare swivel accelerator pedal, patented by Pat Au back in the early 1900s.

Production of the De Luxe Eight was less than ten per day.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1930/1930%20Packard%20Ad-05.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; It was available in eleven body styles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1931/1931%20Packard%20Ad-10.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1930, the Eight was factory priced between US$2425 and US$2885 for the Standard Eight, US$3190 to US$3885 for the Custom Eight, and US$4585 to US$5350.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1930/1930%20Packard%20Ad-08.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1932, prices ranged from US$2250 to US$3250&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-10.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; for the Standard Eight, while the De Luxe Eight started at US$3150.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-19.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Packard Speedster Eight Model 734 was a sporty passenger car line by the Packard Motor Car Company offered for the 1930 model year (7th series) only. Based on a heavily modified Standard Eight (733) chassis, it got smaller and narrower coachwork. The 734 straight eight engine is derived from the 740 Custom Eight's. It differs in valve and manifold revisions, a dual updraft carburetor, a vacuum booster pump and a ribbed exhaust manifold. The engine delivers 145 HP (740: 106 HP) without increase in bore or stroke, which remain at 3½ x 5 in.

Speedster Eights have four instead of three speeds, and the customer could choose from several rear end ratios at no extra cost. 734 models have their parking lights mounted on the fenders, not on the body like Standard Eights. They also feature senior car's hoods with for ventilation door. Only 117 cars were built.

Available 734 Speedster Eight models include:

Body style #422 Boattail Roadster
Body style #443 Sedan
Body style #445 Phaeton
Body style #447 Victoria
Body style #452 Runabout

In 1931, Packard introduced the '''Continental Eight''' and the '''Continental Eight Deluxe''', which were longer wheelbases of the Standard Eight. Period advertisements showed examples with body colored radiator grilles whereas the Standard models had chrome grilles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Packard 1931|url=http://www.classiccarcatalogue.com/PACKARD%201931.html|website=Classic Car Catalog|accessdate=23 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1932 Standard Eight was offered in thirteen body styles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1932/1932%20Packard%20Ad-10.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1933, base price of the Standard Eight was US$2150,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1933/1933%20Packard%20Ad-01.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!--[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1933/1933%20Packard%20Ad-06.jpg This] puts it at US$2350.--&gt; and was offered in fourteen body styles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1933/1933%20Packard%20Ad-03.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; The 1933 De Luxe Eight started at US$3350.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1933/1933%20Packard%20Ad-06.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

The five-passenger sedan was Packard's best-selling model for years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1931/1931%20Packard%20Ad-07.jpg Old Car Advertising] Retrieved 14 September 2013&lt;/ref&gt; This helped Packard become the best-selling luxury brand between 1924 and 1930,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1931/1931%20Packard%20Ad-04.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as selling almost twice as many abroad as any other marque priced over US$2000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcaradvertising.com/Packard%20Ads/1931/1931%20Packard%20Ad-11.jpg Old Car Advertising]. Retrieved 16 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
Flickr_-_DVS1mn_-_27_Packard_by_Murphy_(2).jpg|1927 Packard Eight Model 343 Convertible Sedan by Murphy
Packard De Luxe Eight 904 Sedan Limousine 1932.jpg|1932 De Luxe Eight 904 sedan limousine
Packard 1101 Eight Convertible Sedan 1934.jpg|1934 Standard Eight 1101 convertible sedan
1930 Packard Eight Series 734 Speedster Roadster, Greenwich (front left).jpg|1930 Packard Eight Series 734 Speedster Roadster
File:Concours d'Elegance (20646864791).jpg|1930 Packard type 734 Boattail Speedster
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Commons category|Packard Eight}}
{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Eight]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]
[[Category:1930s cars]]</text>
      <sha1>pz8n869y9erz92bnfe2dm4qo9hi6pni</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Studebaker-Packard Hawk series</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>667199</id>
    <revision>
      <id>894920308</id>
      <parentid>894919751</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-04-30T20:55:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Akld guy</username>
        <id>3122361</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rewrite extravagant [[WP:POV]] opinions</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="6034" xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=December 2009}}
The '''Studebaker-Packard Hawk series''' were [[automobile|cars]] produced by the merged [[Studebaker]]-[[Packard]] corporation between 1956 and 1964.  All but the 1958 Packard Hawk were badged Studebaker.  Described by the company as "family sports cars", they were all two-door, four-seat coupes and hardtops. They were an evolution of the long wheelbase (120") 1953 C/K models designed by Robert Bourke, lead designer with the Raymond Loewy Agency.  The 1962 redesign as the GT Hawk was by another famed stylist, Brooks Stevens.

The precursor of the Hawks was the 1955 Studebaker Speedster, a special edition hardtop with stainless steel trim above the rear window, usually fog lights on the front bumper, deluxe leather interior. a special dash and unique two tone paint combinations.  The success of the Speedster led to the expanded line of 1956 Hawks.

{| style="border: solid" rules="all" align="center"
|+'''Timeline of the Hawk models'''
!Model!!1956!!1957!!1958!!1959!!1960!!1961!!1962!!1963!!1964
|-
|[[Studebaker Flight Hawk|Flight Hawk]]||align="center"|X||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[Studebaker Power Hawk|Power Hawk]]||align="center"|X||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[Studebaker Sky Hawk|Sky Hawk]]||align="center"|X||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[Studebaker Golden Hawk|Golden Hawk]]||align="center"|X||align="center"|X||align="center"|X||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[Studebaker Silver Hawk|Silver Hawk]]||&amp;nbsp;||align="center"|X||align="center"|X||align="center"|X||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[Packard Hawk]]||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||align="center"|X||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[Studebaker Hawk|Hawk]]||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||align="center"|X||align="center"|X||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[Studebaker Gran Turismo Hawk|Gran Turismo Hawk]]||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;||align="center"|X||align="center"|X||align="center"|X
|}

The four-model Hawk range launched in 1956, mirrored the engine and trim levels of the sedans.  There were two coupes; the [[Studebaker Flight Hawk|Flight Hawk]] was a base model powered by [[Studebaker Champion|Champion]]'s obsolete and underpowered flathead [[straight-6]] enlarged to 185.6"; the [[Studebaker Power Hawk|Power Hawk]] used Studebaker's mid-level OHV 259" with either {{Convert|180|hp|abbr=on}} 2-bbl or {{Convert|195|hp|abbr=on}} with a 4-bbl in (4.7 L) [[V8 engine|V8]] from the [[Studebaker Commander|Commander]]; there were two hardtops; the [[Studebaker Sky Hawk|Sky Hawk]] shared the larger OHV 289 in³ V8 and luxury trim with the [[Studebaker President]] and [[Studebaker Golden Hawk]], however, stood at the top of the range. The Golden Hawk, fitted with Packard's powerful [[big-block V8|big-block]] 352 cubic inch 275&amp;nbsp;hp (5.8 L) V8, was the best all-around high performance car of 1956.  Some feel by installing the largest V8 in the smallest lightest body, Studebaker created the first muscle car eight years before the GTO.  It had the second highest power-to-weight ratio of any American production car.  Contemporary road tests verified the Golden Hawk was faster/quicker in the 1/4 mile than the Corvette, Thunderbird and Chrysler 300B.  In top speed, only the Chrysler 300B could equal it.

By 1956, Studebaker-Packard's financial condition had deteriorated to the point where there was no choice but to discontinue all manufacturing in the Packard facilities.  Packard's Detroit factory and Utica proving grounds were closed. In a stop-gap effort to buy time for the development and financing of an all-new Packard, and to honor existing dealer contracts, a 1957 Packard that was merely a dressed up Studebaker President went into production at Studebaker's factory in South Bend. As Packard's V8 was no longer being produced, the new Packard as well as the 1957 Golden Hawk were fitted with Studebaker's largest 289 in³ V8, equipped with a McCulloch supercharger to produce the same {{Convert|275|hp|abbr=on}} rated power output as the 1956 Packard V8.  The range was simplified; the Sky Hawk was discontinued as too close to the Golden Hawk, while the two lowest models were replaced with a single [[Studebaker Silver Hawk|Silver Hawk]] model, available with either the Champion straight-6 or 259 cubic inch (4.2 L) V8.  1958 saw a restyled and re-badged luxury version of the Golden Hawk sold as the [[Packard Hawk]].  

Studebaker sales continued a rapid decline in 1957-58, so for 1959 Studebaker-Packard discontinued the hardtop Golden Hawk, all Packards, and the Studebaker sedans; the Silver Hawk coupe was the only holdover left alongside the new [[Studebaker Lark]] range.  It was a make-or-break year, but Studebaker's big gamble paid off; the smaller-appearing Lark was actually just the six-year-old sedans with a shorter wheelbase and abbreviated front and rear sheetmetal, but it was in the right place at the right time, a car the market wanted.  The Silver Hawk served as a useful showroom draw, and it was continued; since it was the only Hawk model left, it was renamed simply the Studebaker Hawk and continued under that name through the end of 1961.

For the 1962 model year, Brooks Stevens restyled the GT Hawk and it was launched as the [[Studebaker Gran Turismo Hawk|Gran Turismo Hawk]].  Its styling was well received, and sold relatively well for 1962.  By 1963, Studebaker sales were in an irreversible death spiral. Even though the 1964 Super Hawk, available with an optional R2 supercharged engine, 4-speed transmission, TwinTraction limited-slip differential, front disc brakes and a sport suspension, was the best Hawk ever, production was ended with the rest of Studebaker's US production in December 1963.

{{Studebaker-Packard_Hawk_series}}
{{Studebaker}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Studebaker-Packard Hawk Series}}
[[Category:Studebaker vehicles|Hawk]]
[[Category:Packard vehicles]]</text>
      <sha1>mon7qlpnbpx4yh4mhcbkimgstoihj6r</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>List of Packard vehicles</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>40840992</id>
    <redirect title="Packard" />
    <revision>
      <id>865485715</id>
      <parentid>736396638</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-24T07:38:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cydebot</username>
        <id>1215485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot - Speedily moving category Lists of automobiles to [[:Category:Lists of cars]] per [[WP:CFDS|CFDS]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="157" xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[Packard#Packard automobile models]]

[[Category:Redirects with possibilities]]
[[Category:Packard vehicles|*]]
[[Category:Lists of cars|Packard]]</text>
      <sha1>eqhqmaolj1pal581ha2te2ktmwqvkzq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Pacific</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>44959698</id>
    <revision>
      <id>878246989</id>
      <parentid>865502034</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-01-13T21:53:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Typ932</username>
        <id>3709252</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Script assisted. Units/dates/other/ per [[WP:AUN]], [[User:Typ932/monobook.js|Script]]-assisted. Units/dates/other</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4783" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox automobile
| name              = Packard Pacific
| image             = 1954 Packard Pacific.jpg
| caption           = 1954 Packard Pacific
| manufacturer = [[Packard]]
| model_years   = 1954
| assembly        = [[Packard Automotive Plant]], [[Detroit]], [[Michigan]], [[United States]]
| class               = [[Full-size car|Full-size]] [[Luxury vehicle|luxury car]] 
| body_style      = 2-door [[hardtop]]
| layout             = [[Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive layout|Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive]] 
| engine             = {{convert|359|cuin|L|1|abbr=on}} 4-bbl. [[Flathead engine|L-head]] [[Straight-eight engine|I8]] (212 hp)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Flory, Jr.|first=J. "Kelly"|title=American Cars, 1946-1959 Every Model Every Year|year=2008|publisher=McFarland &amp; Company, Inc., Publishers|isbn=978-0-7864-3229-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| transmission   = 2-speed ''[[Ultramatic#1949-1954: Ultramatic Drive|Ultramatic]]'' [[Automatic transmission|automatic]]
| wheelbase      = {{convert|122|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}
| length             = {{convert|211.5|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}
| width              = {{convert|77.9|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}
| height             = {{convert|62|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name="classic"&gt;{{cite web|title=1954 Packard Pacific &amp; Caribbean Series 5431 Mayfair Hardtop Coupe|url=http://www.classiccardatabase.com/specs.php?series=5122&amp;year=1954&amp;model=28104|website=Classic Car Database|accessdate=4 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| weight             = {{convert|4040|lb|kg|0|abbr=on}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=5477 Packard Pacific Hardtop|url=http://packardinfo.com/xoops/html/modules/modelinfo/viewmodel.php?model=33|website=Packardinfo.com|accessdate=4 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| predecessor   = [[Packard Mayfair]]
| successor       = [[Packard Four Hundred]]
}}

The '''Packard Pacific''' is an automobile manufactured by the [[Packard|Packard Motor Car Company]] of [[Detroit]], [[Michigan]] for the 1954 model year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Langworth|first=Richard M.| title=Illustrated Packard Buyer's Guide: All Packard Cars and Commercial Vehicles, 1899 to 1958| publisher=Motorbooks International|year=1991|isbn=0-87938-427-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; It replaced the [[Packard Mayfair|Mayfair]] and was sold exclusively as a two-door [[hardtop]].

In the early 1950s, Packard used a numeric naming scheme that designated Packard's least expensive models as the [[Packard 200]] and 200 Deluxe, while two-door hardtops and [[Convertible (car)|convertible]]s were designated Packard 250 and its mid-range sedan the [[Packard 300]]. For model years 1951 through 1953, the 250 hardtop was named the Mayfair; for model year 1954 only, the hardtop was given the model name '''Pacific'''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Consumer Guide|first=Auto Editors of|title=50 Years of American Automobiles|year=1989|publisher=Beekman House|isbn=0-517-68640-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mayfair, Packard's first hardtop offering, was created for the 1951 model year in order to keep in competition with [[Cadillac]], [[Buick]], and [[Chrysler Imperial|Imperial]] from [[Chrysler]], whose hardtop sales were booming. The Mayfair was named after the exclusive [[Mayfair]] district of [[London]].  In renaming it as the Pacific, Packard associated the model with its [[personal luxury car]] offering, the [[Packard Caribbean|Caribbean]].  Both the Mayfair and Pacific shared the same [[straight-eight engine]]s (a 327-cubic inch for the Mayfair and a 359-cubic inch for the Pacific)&lt;ref&gt;Consumer Guide, pp. 637-638&lt;/ref&gt; with top-of-the-line, or "senior" Packards, but were mounted on the {{convert|122|in|mm|sing=on}} wheelbase of less expensive, or "junior" models. The Pacific came standard-equipped with Packard's [[Ultramatic]] automatic transmission.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=1954 Salesmen Facts Book – Packard and Packard Clipper|date=1954|publisher=Packard Motor Car Company|page=137|url=http://packardinfo.com/xoops/html/downloads/SalesFactBook54.pdf|accessdate=4 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Pacific and Mayfair were distinguished by high levels of interior trim: for instance, leather upholstery was provided, and the cars' interior headliners were ornamented with chrome strips intended to suggest a convertible top. The cars were also given innovative exterior color schemes; most were given two-tone paint jobs (for example: "Carnation" (white) and "Amethyst" (lavender)), which were considered fashionable at the time.&lt;ref&gt;Langworth, p. 110&lt;/ref&gt;

1,189 Pacific hardtops were built before production concluded for the 1954 model year.&lt;ref name="classic" /&gt; Starting in 1955, Packard renamed its senior hardtop the [[Packard Four Hundred|Four Hundred]].

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Pacific]]
[[Category:Coupés]]
[[Category:Cars introduced in 1954]]
[[Category:1950s cars]]</text>
      <sha1>ijuxdif6bhmf80sbg72ucr80srr8dz7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard 250</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>36469066</id>
    <redirect title="Packard 200" />
    <revision>
      <id>680602723</id>
      <parentid>502912757</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-09-11T23:18:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GTHO</username>
        <id>3613546</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[Category:Packard vehicles|250]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="60" xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[Packard 200]]

[[Category:Packard vehicles|250]]</text>
      <sha1>i25ovnxc3vqrx4vqkoq0kqmxwarot4e</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Model G</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32465695</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931490653</id>
      <parentid>914683918</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-19T05:16:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelinking 1 books for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.1alpha3</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="7132" xml:space="preserve">'''Packard Model G''' is a two [[cylinder (engine)|cylinder]] car built in 1902 by the former American automobile manufacturer [[Packard|Ohio Automobile Company]] that changed name to '''Packard Motor Car Company''' in October, 1902.

At that time the company was located in [[Warren, Ohio]]; owners were brothers [[James Ward Packard]] and [[William Doud Packard]] and [[investor]] [[George Lewis Weiss]]. Model G was a development of the former single-cylinder cars the company had built since 1899 of which the last, [[Packard Single-Cylinder|Model F]], was offered alongside the Model G. Introduction was in late summer 1902. Only four cars were built.

== Chassis ==
The pressed steel frame of the Model G was new although it followed earlier principles. With a wheelbase of 91 in. (2,311&amp;nbsp;mm) it was the longest yet. [[Axle track|Track]] was 56 in. (1,422&amp;nbsp;mm), in fact 0.5 in. (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) less than Model F's. The car had the then-usual right hand steering. It was among the first US automobiles that featured a [[steering wheel]] instead of a [[tiller]].

Road [[wheel]]s were non-detachable and of the [[artillery wheel]] type. Each had 14 wood [[spoke]]s. Front and rear wheels had the same dimensions with 36 x 4.5 in. pneumatic tires. Model G had very big wheels hubs which gave the car a characteristic look. [[Suspension (vehicle)|Suspension]] consisted of a semi-[[elliptical]] [[leaf spring]]s in front and elliptical at the rear. There were two brakes; one actuated the transmission by a lever outside of the bodywork that actuated, the other, operated by pedal, the [[Differential (mechanical device)|differential]].

== Engine and Transmission ==
As with all Packards to date, the Model G's engine was placed under the driver's bench and laterally mounted, the crank protruding out of the right side. As mentioned, it was derived from the single-cylinder variant for which Packard already had a good reputation. Construction consisted of two single-cylinder engines that were connected in a horizontal opposed position and worked 
on a common [[crank shaft]]. Blocks were cast iron with non-detachable [[cylinder head]]s. Cylinders had a bore and stroke of 6 x 6 1/2 in. (152.4 × 165.1&amp;nbsp;mm) each, resulting in a displacement of 184 c.i (3,015&amp;nbsp;cm³) per cylinder and huge 368 c.i. (6,030&amp;nbsp;cm³) for the whole engine. Packard used a ''Longuemar'' [[Carburetor|float-feed carburetor]] for each cylinder. [[Ignition advance]] was manual. Power rating (following then-actual practice) was 24 H.P.

As introduced with the Model F, Model G also adopted a front-mounted, tough bigger, radiator. This led the car appear, together with the storage place behind it, as a front-engined automobile.

Gearbox was sliding gear, with three speeds forward plus reverse. Power transmission to the rear wheels worked via a single, center mounted [[chain drive|chain]] which itself was connected to the differential.

== Coachwork ==
Model G was a huge car for the time, weighing in at about {{convert|4000|lb}}. Packard offered it with two body styles: Either as a four-passenger [[Surrey (carriage)|Surrey]] or an eight-passenger Tonneau (sometimes called a "Rear Tonneau Roadster"). The surrey had neither front nor rear doors and came with two forward-facing benches. The tonneau had one bench in front plus two more placed longitudally. Access to the ladder was by a small door in the rear. There were no front doors. Coachwork was made of high quality using wood, probably by a local carriage builder as with other Packards. The customer had a free choice of colors. Upholstery was of qual quality, executed with top grain leather.

Included with the base price were a pair of ''Dietz'' oil lamps, a ''Speed-O-Meter'', and gauges for fuel and oil, each installed on the respective tank. An ignition switch was optional. The actual MSRP is not known but considering the smaller Model F tonneau being priced at $2,500 it is a close guess that the more complex Model G cost over $3,000.

== Appreciation ==
While in 1902 alone, 179 Packard Model F left the plant in Warren, only 4 Model G were built. It marked a high- and terminal point for the Ohio Automobile Co. in many ways. It was the last Packard vastly developed by chief engineer and vice president ''Wiliam A. Hatcher'' who left the company January 17, 1903 because he did not agree with the direction the company took. His successor, Frenchman ''Charles Schmidt'' lead Packard to more modern, European construction principles.

Technically, Model G represents the end of the first generation Packards as it was the make's last [[Horse and buggy|buggy-styled]] passenger car (with the engine positioned under the driver's bench), the last with the noisy and not very reliable chain drive and, most important, the last with less than four cylinders. For a long time, J. W. Packard had been convinced that the single-cylinder engine was the power plant of the future. When it became obvious that the industry would lead another way, Packard followed suit with four-cylinder automobiles already in 1903. Thus, Model G remained the only passenger car with a twin (there also were some two-cylinder trucks), survived by the Model F by another year.

One of the customers who bought a Model G was [[William Rockefeller]], younger brother of [[John D. Rockefeller]]. Of the four Model G's built, one still exists in a private collection. It is a surrey with a canopy and painted red.

==References==
* {{cite book |title=Packard, a history of the motor car and the company |editor-first=Beverly Rae |editor-last=Kimes |editor-link=Beverly Rae Kimes |year=1978 |publisher=Automobile Quarterly |isbn=0-915038-11-0}}
* {{cite book |title=The Standard Catalogue of American Cars, 1805-1942 |editor-first=Beverly Rae |editor-last=Kimes |editor-link=Beverly Rae Kimes |first=Henry Austin, Jr. |last=Clark |edition=2nd |year=1985 |publisher=[[Krause Publications]] |location=Iola, Wisconsin |isbn=0-87341-111-0 |page=[https://archive.org/details/standardcatalogo0000kime/page/1066 1066] |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/standardcatalogo0000kime/page/1066 }}
* "Packard", George H. Dammann und James A. Wren Motorbooks International, Crestline Series, Osceola WI, {{ISBN|0-7603-0104-2}}
* The Packard Identification Guide Volume One", Dr. Robert B. Marvin; 2t. Auflage; R-Mac Publications (1990)

== External links ==
{{commonscat|Packard vehicles}}
* [http://www.packardclub.org/ PAC Packard Automobile Classics]
* [http://packardinfo.com/xoops/html/modules/modelinfo/viewmodel.php?model=224 Packard Information; short description of the Model G]; shows a surrey that is mistakingly called the "Rear Tonneau Roadster".
* [http://packardinfo.com/xoops/html/modules/myalbum/viewcat.php?cid=6 Packard Information Photo Archive]; pictures 9, 10, 11 and 14 show Model G (14 shows William Rockefeller's surrey).

{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Model G]]
[[Category:Cars introduced in 1902]]
[[Category:1900s cars]]
[[Category:Veteran vehicles]]
[[Category:Rear_mid-engine,_rear-wheel-drive_vehicles]]</text>
      <sha1>gw2xhg429fjiuo77nl217rs1f4iublj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Model 30 (series U)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33294939</id>
    <revision>
      <id>929489229</id>
      <parentid>929487197</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-06T04:29:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Dubious}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="3749" xml:space="preserve">{{see also|Packard Model 30}}
The '''Packard Model 30''' frequently also called '''Model U''', was a four-cylinder car built in several series from 1907-1912. Together with the smaller Model 18 (1908-1912), it was [[Packard]]'s last four-cylinder [[automobile]]. Model 30 was Packard's lone offering for 1907 and 1908. It established Packard as a luxury car maker, and was replaced by the [[Packard Six]].

== Model history ==

The Packard Model 30 was a four-cylinder car with both closed and open bodies. Prices at introduction started with $4200 for open models and went up to $5500 for the [[limousine]] and $5600 for the [[Landaulet (car)|landaulet]].&lt;ref name="PI Model info_1907"&gt;packardinfo.com: Model Information/1907&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="PAC_1907"&gt;packardclub.org: Encyclopedia/1907&lt;/ref&gt; A 1911 Four-door Landaulet cost $5,750.&lt;ref name="oldcarbrochures"&gt;[http://www.oldcarbrochures.com/static/NA/Packard/1911_Packard/1911_Packard_Owners_Manual/1911%20Packard%20Manual-010-011.html Directory Index: Packard/1911_Packard/1911_Packard_Owners_Manual&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Standard equipment included oil lamps, a tool kit, and two extra demountable rims. The closed cars also included [[speaking tube]]s, adjustable ventilators, and a dome light that had a separate battery. There was a [[speedometer]] and an air-pressure gauge. [[Wheelbase]] was 123 1/2" for the standard chassis.

== Engine  and drivetrain==
The Packard Model 30 had a [[Internal combustion engine cooling|water-cooled]], four-cylinder, [[T-head engine]] with a calculated rating of
30&amp;nbsp;hp ([[Association of Licensed Automobile Manufacturers|A.L.A.M.]]) at 650 [[Revolutions per minute|rpm]].{{dubious|date=December 2019}}&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=kdz7AAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA35&amp;dq=%22a.l.a.m.%22+automobile+horsepower&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiSi4PWkaDmAhW26XMBHU47DQgQ6AEIKDAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22a.l.a.m.%22%20automobile%20horsepower&amp;f=false ''American Automobiles of the Brass Era'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="oldcarbrochures" /&gt; displacing 431.9 [[cubic inch]]es (7078 [[cubic centimeter]]s)&lt;ref name="PI Model info_1907"/&gt; with a bore 5 in (127&amp;nbsp;mm) and a stroke of 5.5 in (139.7&amp;nbsp;mm).&lt;ref name="PAC_1907"/&gt;

A plate [[clutch]] was blocked with the engine. Power was transmitted by a long shaft with [[universal joint]]s to the three-speed sliding-gear [[manual gearbox]] with reverse. This was located in a housing at the rear axle which also contained the [[Differential (mechanical device)|differential]]. The car used shaft drive from the beginning, although many other high-powered cars at this time relied on double-[[chain drive]].

In 1909, redesigned linkage in the transmission made it possible for the reverse gear to be activated with the regular gear-shift. Since 1904, all Packards had had a separate lever for the reverse gear.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kimes|first=Beverly|title=standard catalog of American Cars 1805-1942|year=1996|publisher=Krause publications|isbn=0-87341-428-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Chassis ==
The ladder-type frame used semielliptical [[leaf spring]]s front and rear. Steering included now [[ball bearing]]s instead of roller types, and featured a [[Pitman arm]] in front of the front axle.&lt;ref name="PI Model info_1907"/&gt;&lt;ref name="PAC_1907"/&gt;

Brakes were mechanical on the rear wheels only, working either by pedal (external contracting) or lever ([[Drum brake|internal expanding]]). Following the owner's manual, either was sufficient for stopping under normal conditions.&lt;ref name="OwnersManual1911_92-93"&gt;Owner's Manual 1911, pp. 92-93&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="OwnersManual1911_28"&gt;Owner's Manual 1911, p. 28&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{commonscat}}
{{reflist}}
{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Model 30]]</text>
      <sha1>pfevgavnbya166blc90wkiwsj0q1t0a</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Flintstone Flyer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>53864943</id>
    <revision>
      <id>869523991</id>
      <parentid>866779577</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-19T04:13:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Trekphiler</username>
        <id>601623</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>reword a bit (add notability to lead?)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2467" xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:''Flintstone Flyer''}}
'''''Flintstone Flyer''''' is a  [[Chevrolet Corvette (C1)|Corvette]]-powered 1949 [[Packard]] [[Gasser (car)|gasser]] of the 1960s, built and driven by [[Dave Koffel]].&lt;ref&gt;Davis, Larry. ''Gasser Wars'' (Cartech, 2003), pp.13 and 180-8.&lt;/ref&gt; It set one national claas record (in 1961) and won two class titles (1962 and 1963).&lt;ref&gt;Davis, pp.13 and 183.&lt;/ref&gt;
==History==
The car was a dark blue 1949 Packard, purchased for US$50 and built in Koffel's own garage.&lt;ref&gt;Davis, p.13.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The engine was [[Engine swap|swapped]] for a {{convert|292|cid|cc|abbr=on}} [[Chevrolet small-block engine|Chevrolet small-block V8]] (from a 1961 [[Chevrolet Corvette (C1)|Corvette]], bored {{convert|0.060|in|mm|abbr=on}} over).  It was only mildly modified, fitted with 270 heads, solid-[[Valve lifter|lifter]] [[camshaft]], and [[Offenhauser]] [[intake manifold]] (with three two-barrel {twin-choke} [[carburetor]]s).&lt;ref&gt;Davis, p.13.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Transmission (mechanics)|transmission]] was a four-speed manual from a Corvette, and the rear axle came from a 1957 [[Plymouth (automobile)|Plymouth]] with a steep 6.17:1 ratio (because of the car's high weight, {{convert|4430|lb|kg|abbr=on}}).&lt;ref&gt;Davis, p.13.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1961, Koffel changed the [[Hot rod#Language|three deuces]] to [[Stuart Hilborn|Hilborn]] [[fuel injection]].&lt;ref&gt;Davis, p.13.&lt;/ref&gt; In this trim, the car set a new [[National Hot Rod Association|NHRA]] national record in E/G at 13.33 seconds and {{convert|104.04|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;Davis, p.13.&lt;/ref&gt; 

It won the 1962 E/G national title at the [[1962 NHRA Nationals|NHRA Nationals]], [[Indianapolis Raceway Park]], with a pass of 13.71 seconds at {{convert|102.85|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;Davis, p.183.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1963, Koffel replaced the steel front end panels with custom [[fiberglass]] items produced by Walt Sari of [[Ashtabula, Ohio]].&lt;ref&gt;Davis, p.13.&lt;/ref&gt;  With the fiberglass panels fitted, '''Flintstone Flyer'' won the 1963 F/G national title at the [[1963 NHRA Nationals|NHRA Nationals]] in Indianapolis, with a pass of 13.69 seconds at {{convert|101.80|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;Davis, p.183.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==Sources==
*Davis, Larry. ''Gasser Wars'', North Branch, MN:  Cartech, 2003, pp.180-8.

{{motorsports-stub}}
{{automobile-stub}}
[[Category:Packard vehicles]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]
[[Category:1940s cars]]
[[Category:1960s cars]]
[[Category:Drag racing cars]]</text>
      <sha1>7cmd5cm92685bfk35em0mc9plzn0rrh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Packard Twelve</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>62074103</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941403655</id>
      <parentid>931490717</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-18T11:10:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2A02:C7D:3FB0:300:9803:2801:14A4:C90E</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Trivia */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="9271" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox automobile
| name           = Packard Super Eight
| image          = 1939 Packard Twelve Coupé in Belfair Green, front left side (Hershey 2019).jpg
| caption        = 1939 Packard Twelve Coupe (1707)
| manufacturer   = [[Packard]]
| model_years    = 1933–1939
| assembly       = [[Packard Automotive Plant]], [[Detroit]], [[Michigan]], [[United States]]
| layout         = [[Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive layout|Front-engine, rear-wheel-drive]]
| related        = {{ubl | [[Packard Super Eight]] | [[Packard Twin Six]] }}
| engine         = {{ubl | {{convert|445.5|CID|L|1|abbr=on}} [[V12 engine|V12]] (1933-1934) | {{convert|473.3|CID|L|1|abbr=on}} V12 (1935-1939) }}
| body_style     = {{unbulleted list|2-door [[coupé]]|2/4-door [[Convertible (car)|convertible]]|4-door [[Sedan (automobile)|sedan]]}}
| wheelbase      = {{unbulleted list|{{convert|127+3/8|in|mm|0|abbr=on}} (1938) | {{convert|132+1/2|in|m|2|abbr=on}} (1935-1937) | {{convert|134+3/8|in|m|2|abbr=on}} (1938-1939) | {{convert|135|in|m|2|abbr=on}} (1934) | {{convert|139+1/4|in|m|2|abbr=on}} (1935-1937)  {{convert|139+3/8|in|m|2|abbr=on}} (1938-1939) | {{convert|142|in|m|2|abbr=on}} (1933-1934) | {{convert|144+1/4|in|m|2|abbr=on}} (1935-1937) | {{convert|147|in|m|2|abbr=on}} (1933-1934) }}
| length         = 
| predecessor    = [[Packard Twin Six]]
| successor      = none
}}

The '''Packard Twelve''' was a range of [[V12 engine|V12-engined]] luxury automobiles built by the [[Packard|Packard Motor Car Company]] in [[Detroit]], [[Michigan]]. The car was built from model year 1933 until 1939 as a successor to the twelve-cylinder [[Packard Twin Six|Twin Six]]. As a sign of changing times, the majority of Packard Twelves received standard bodywork, with custom bodywork gradually losing favor. Many of the custom cars were actually only "semi-customs", with [[Dietrich Inc.|Dietrich]] assembling Packard-made bodies with special touches.&lt;ref name=about1&gt;{{cite web | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20190711042155/https://ateupwithmotor.com/model-histories/packard-twelve-twin-six-history/3/ | archivedate = 2019-07-11 | url = https://ateupwithmotor.com/model-histories/packard-twelve-twin-six-history/3/ | title = Counting to Twelve: The Packard Twelve and Twin Six | work = Ate Up With Motor | date = 2010-06-26 | last = Severson | first = Aaron }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
[[File:1933 Packard 1005 Convertible Coupe - svr (12824103524).jpg|thumb|left|1933 Packard 1005 Convertible Coupé]]

For 1933 Packard updated the 1932 Twin Six and switched its name to "Packard Twelve," to align it with the rest of the Packard lineup.&lt;ref name=CCZ1106&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.conceptcarz.com/vehicle/z9059/packard-1106-twelve.aspx | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20150913160519/http://www.conceptcarz.com/vehicle/z9059/Packard-1106-Twelve.aspx | archivedate = 2015-09-13 | title = 1934 Packard 1106 Twelve | last = Vaughan | first = Daniel | date = April 2008 | work = ConceptCarz.com }}&lt;/ref&gt; This was the 10th Series and two models were on offer: the 1005 and the 1006 had wheelbases of {{convert|142|in|m|2|abbr=on}} and {{convert|147|in|m|2|abbr=on}}. The Twin Six' double drop frame was replaced by a tapered design.&lt;ref name=Ind238&gt;[[#Indie|''Standard Catalog of Independents'']], p. 238&lt;/ref&gt; Convertibles and roadsters used leftover ninth series bodies with a smaller radiator than the all-new tenth series models.&lt;ref name=about1/&gt;

The Twin Six' V12-engine was retained without major change. The cylinder blocks are at a 67 degree angle, bore and stroke {{convert|3+7/16|and|4|in|mm|1|abbr=on}} respectively. A {{convert|445.5|CID|cc|0|abbr=on}} displacement was the result and maximum power is {{convert|160|hp|kW|0|abbr=on}} at 3200&amp;nbsp;rpm. The cooling system was improved and a new Bendix-Stromberg EE-3 carburetor with an automatic choke was introduced, increasing power somewhat. A single dry-plate clutch replaced the earlier twin-plate model, matched to a floor-shifted three-speed manual transmission and a new one-piece driveshaft. The existing mechanical brakes were also adopted for the Twelve.

The shorter wheelbase (Model 1005) was available with at least ten different styles of bodywork, ranging from the two-seat Coupe Roadster to the five-seat Formal Sedan. Standard bodyworks for the long wheelbase Model 1006 were Sedan and Sedan Limousine (both either five- or seven-seaters), with a host of custom bodyworks also on offer. These were mainly by [[Dietrich Inc.|Dietrich]] and [[LeBaron Incorporated|LeBaron]]. The Super Eight long wheelbase chassis was no longer available, restricting custom bodyworks to the new Twelve.&lt;ref name=Ind238/&gt;

=== Year-to-year changes ===
In 1934 the 11th series model was introduced, adding a shorter third version on the {{convert|135|in|m|2|abbr=on}} chassis of the [[Packard Super Eight|Super Eight]].&lt;ref name=Ind239&gt;[[#Indie|''Standard Catalog of Independents'']], p. 239&lt;/ref&gt; An "Aero Sport Coupe" bodied in-house and a [[LeBaron Incorporated|LeBaron]]-bodied "Runabout Speedster" were available on this wheelbase; only around ten of these two types were made. The appearance of the dramatic, almond-shaped Aero Sport Coupe was guided by Packard stylist Ed Macauley although the actual design work was done by Count [[Alexis de Sakhnoffsky]] in his stint as a consultant at Packard. Only four Sport Coupes were built. This was the last car to be "Custom Made by Packard."&lt;ref name=CCZ1106/&gt; The Model codes were 1106 (short), 1107 (middle), and 1108 (long). 960 Packard Twelves were built in 1934. This was also the first year that a radio was a factory option.

[[File:Packard 1108 Twelve Dietrich Convertible Victoria 1934.jpg|thumb|left|Packard 1108 Twelve Dietrich Convertible Victoria 1934]]
For the 12th Series of 1935, the engine gained aluminum heads and was stroked by a quarter inch, bringing up the displacement to {{convert|473.3|CID|cc|0|abbr=on}}. Power is {{convert|175|hp|kW|0|abbr=on}} at 3200&amp;nbsp;rpm and a high compression version with {{convert|180|hp|kW|0|abbr=on}} was also available. The gearbox was now fully synchronized and both the mechanical brakes and the clutch received [[Vacuum servo|vacuum assist]]. The new wheelbases on offer were {{convert|132+1/2|in|m|2|abbr=on}}, {{convert|139+1/4|in|m|2|abbr=on}}, and {{convert|144+1/4|in|m|2|abbr=on}}. The 14th Series of 1936 was largely unchanged from the 12th (there was no [[Triskaidekaphobia|13th]] Series). The only differences were a radiator angled by five more degrees, the oil temperature regulator was redesigned, and the shortest wheelbase model was discontinued.&lt;ref name=Ind243&gt;[[#Indie|''Standard Catalog of Independents'']], p. 243&lt;/ref&gt;

Model year 1937 brought hydraulic brakes for the 15th Series Twelve; these had already been available for two years on the [[Packard One-Twenty|Packard One Twenty]].&lt;ref name=Ind240&gt;[[#Indie|''Standard Catalog of Independents'']], p. 240&lt;/ref&gt; [[Suicide door]]s were changed to conventional, front-hinged ones. With 1300 built, 1937 was the Twelve's most successful year.&lt;ref name=Ind245&gt;[[#Indie|''Standard Catalog of Independents'']], p. 245&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:1936_Packard_V-12_Speedster_(5624610192).jpg|thumb|right|1936 Packard Twelve Speedster Boattail]]
1938's 16th Series brought yet shorter wheelbases: {{convert|127+3/8|in|m|2|abbr=on}}, {{convert|134+3/8|in|m|2|abbr=on}}, and {{convert|139+3/8|in|m|2|abbr=on}}. The shortest Model 1606 used the Super Eight chassis but was not included in Packard's brochures and it is unsure if any were built.&lt;ref name=Ind247&gt;[[#Indie|''Standard Catalog of Independents'']], p. 247&lt;/ref&gt; Only 566 16th Series Twelves were built, followed by 446 17th Series. The fenders were of a heavier design than on previous years' models, while a column shift became and option alongside the center mounted shifter. This shape remained in use for 1939's 17th Series, the last of the Packard Twelves. 5262 examples were built in total. For 1940 Packard's top model was the [[Packard Super Eight]].

== Trivia ==
In October 1935, American President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] gave [[Joseph Stalin]] an armoured Packard Twelve, which became the dictator's favourite automotive vehicle for many years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.rbth.com/lifestyle/328376-kremlin-cars-favorite-rides | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20190618210059/https://www.rbth.com/lifestyle/328376-kremlin-cars-favorite-rides | archivedate = 2019-06-18 | title = Kremlin cars: The favorite rides of Russian leaders, from Nicholas II to Putin | work = Russia Beyond | publisher =  | last = Timofeychev | first = Aleksey | date = 2018-05-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
* {{Cite book | title = Standard Catalog of Independents: The Struggle to Survive Among Giants | editor-first = Ron | editor-last = Kowalke | publisher = Krause Publications | ref = Indie | location = Iola, WI | pages = [https://archive.org/details/standardcatalogo00ronk/page/238 238-248] | date = 1999 | isbn = 0-87341-569-8 | url = https://archive.org/details/standardcatalogo00ronk/page/238 }}

{{commonscat}}
{{Packard}}
{{Packard historic timeline}}

[[Category:Packard vehicles|Twelve]]
[[Category:Rear-wheel-drive vehicles]]
[[Category:Cars introduced in 1933]]</text>
      <sha1>dlt1369cbyz13i4m7hfc7xzr835cebk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
